<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The summe of the foure Euangelistes comprehending both the course of the historie, and also the seuerall points of doctrine set foorth in the same pointing foorth as it were with the hand, that Iesus is Christ, the only, perfect, and sufficient Sauiour of all the faithfull. Written in Latine by the reuerend, learned, and godly father, Master Henrie Bullinger minister of the Church of Zurich. Translated into English for the profite of the vnlearned by Iohn Tomkys.</title>
            <author>Bullinger, Heinrich, 1504-1575.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1582</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 207 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 75 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17221</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4077</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118851</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854058</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854058</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19465</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17221)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19465)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 412:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The summe of the foure Euangelistes comprehending both the course of the historie, and also the seuerall points of doctrine set foorth in the same pointing foorth as it were with the hand, that Iesus is Christ, the only, perfect, and sufficient Sauiour of all the faithfull. Written in Latine by the reuerend, learned, and godly father, Master Henrie Bullinger minister of the Church of Zurich. Translated into English for the profite of the vnlearned by Iohn Tomkys.</title>
                  <author>Bullinger, Heinrich, 1504-1575.</author>
                  <author>Tomkys, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[144] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By T. Dawson] for William Ponsonby at the signe of the Bishops head,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1582.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>At foot of title page: Seene and allowed according to her Maiesties iniunctions.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [hand] A-H.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Gospels --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19465:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19465:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Summe of the foure Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſtes comprehending both the courſe of the hiſtorie, and alſo the ſeuerall points of doctrine ſet foorth in the ſame, poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting foorth as it were with the hand, that IESVS <hi>is</hi> CHRIST, the only, perfect, and ſufficient Sauiour of all the faithfull.</p>
            <p>Written in Latine by the reuerend, learned, and godly father, Maſter <hi>Henrie Bullinger</hi> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Church of <hi>Zurich.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tranſlated into Engliſh for the profite of the vnlearned by <hi>Iohn Tomkys.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Matthewe 17.5.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>This is my beloued Sonne, in whom I am well pleaſed, heare yee him.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Seene and allowed according to her Maieſties Iniunctions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Imprinted at London for William Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonby at the ſigne of the Biſhops head. 1582.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19465:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19465:2"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>To the reuerend <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in God, William</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Couentrie and <hi>Liech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fielde.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE materiall temple at Ieruſalem, Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rende Father, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it were very ſtately and ſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, yet was it ſo ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificially framed, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding came to the ſetting vp,<note n="*" place="margin">1. Kin. 6.7.</note> there was neither hammer, nor axe, nor any toole of yron heard in the houſe while it was in building, becauſe the ſtone was hewen perfectly alreadie, before it was brought thither.</p>
            <p>Wherein, although wee haue in great admiration the wiſedome of Solomon, by whoſe direction the building was taken in hand, the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpection
<pb facs="tcp:19465:3"/> of the Lordes, which ouer ſawe the worke, the cunning of the maſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, which ſquared the ſtones, and the plentie of ſtones, which ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed ſo huge a building, yet muſt it needes bee graunted, that the office of thoſe, which caried the ſtone, and tranſported the ſame, from the place, where it was framed, to the place, wher the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple was erected, was great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly neceſſarie, and to very good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in this gorgious work. The like proportion is obſerued in the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the ſpirituall temple of God,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Cor. 3.16 &amp; <hi>1.</hi> Cor. 6.19. 1. Pet. 2.5.</note> which is euery faithfull Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 16.16. &amp; <hi>1.</hi> Pet. 2.7.</note> builded by faith vppon Ieſus Chriſte,<note n="*" place="margin">1. Cor. 3.11</note> beeing the only foundati-of the ſame. For Chriſt, being the wiſe Solomon in deed, directeth the worke by his holy ſpirit, good chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Princes by wholeſome lawes, like good ouerſeers, take order that the work may go forward, lerned &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:19465:3"/> godly preachers, as cunning maſons, continually ſquare plenty of ſtones, that is, make many godly Sermons, &amp; write ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>drie learned bokes perfect<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly agreeing with the ſquare of gods worde,<note n="*" place="margin">Gala. 6.16.</note> the only rule of ſpirituall builders, which beeing tranſlated from tongue into tongue by the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence of interpreters, the porters or cariers in this ſpirituall worke, it commeth to paſſe, that God his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect are builded vp by little and little into a ſpirituall temple for GOD him ſelfe to dwell in, with great quietneſſe of conſcience, whiche although it bee ſenſibly felte in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardelye by the faithfull belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo builded, yet is it not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued outwardly by the wicked ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging worlde, which is no part of this building. Howe greatly the auncient Iſraelites ioyed at the erec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the materiall temple,<note n="*" place="margin">Gala. 6.16.</note> the
<pb facs="tcp:19465:4"/> many oblations,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Kin. 8.61 &amp;c.</note> which Solomon offered to the Lorde, and the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne feaſt, which hee and all the people helde, moſt manifeſtly doe declare. How muche more then ought wee to offer vp vnto God<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.1.</note> the oblations of a godly life, and to ioy continually in our heartes, conſidering that it hath pleaſed him in Ieſus Chriſte to builde vs vp by his holy ſpirite for an holy tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple vnto him ſelfe? Nowe forſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as it is the dutie of euery chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian man in his calling, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his habilitie receiued of the Lorde, to further this ioyful worke, I, (acknowledging other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe mine imbecillitie,) haue tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſported by painefull trauell into mine owne Countrie three ſeuerall ſtones, wel ſquared in a foraine land by that godly and learned builder maſter Henry Bullinger Miniſter of the Churche of Zurich; by tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlating
<pb facs="tcp:19465:4"/> into Engliſh: firſt foorth of Frenche a godly Sermon of the Lordes Supper, then foorth of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, a learned treatiſe touching the worthineſſe of holy Scripture, and laſtly forth of the ſame tongue, this preſent worke inſuyng. What mooued mee to tranſlate the two firſte treatiſes, I haue ſufficiently ſhewed in mine Epiſtles dedicatorie prefixed before the ſame. It reſteth therefore that I declare my purpoſe in this my preſente interprice. I reſt in hope, that thoſe my cuntrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, which haue diligently reade ouer my ſeconde trauayle, (that I ſay nothing of the profect, which they may gather of the firſt,) I meane the diſcourſe of the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of the Scripture &amp;c. haue lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned thereby to haue due regarde of Gods holy worde, as of a moſte ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent treaſure, wherby God ſitting
<pb facs="tcp:19465:5"/> in heauen vouchſafeth to talke with vs dwelling vpon earth: and that they are thereby effectually moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with a feruent deſire to reade the Scripture. Wherefore follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my purpoſe, whiche is accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to my duetie to profite my countrey, and to forder the Lordes building. I haue tranſlated preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the helpe of the vnlearned in reading the Sriptures, The ſumme of the foure Euangeliſtes, wherebie we may learne not onely the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ende of the Goſpelles, which is, that Ieſus is Chriſt, the onely, and ſufficient Sauiour of mankinde, but alſo the perticular purpoſe of euerie Chapter, yea almoſt of euerie verſe. By this direction the vnlearned are not ledde, as are ſuperſtitious pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes, into the labyrinth of obſcure ſchoolemen, to be deuoured by that
<pb facs="tcp:19465:5"/> monſtrous Minotaurus the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Antichriſt, but guided in the pathway, that leadeth to life euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting, to the knowledge of Ieſus Chriſt, by whom wee are deliuered from the tyrannie of the Diuell, and reſtored to the fauour of God. And that the diligent reader might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue by the reading hereof no ſmall profecte, I haue noted in the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, by the direction of the Alpha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beticall letters, thoſe verſes of the text of the Euangeliſtes, from chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to chapter, wherevnto euerie part of this Summe is anſwerable, beſides other notes, (profitable I truſt) whiche there alſo I haue put downe. Much about the tyme, that I finiſhed this my ſimple tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, reuerende Father, your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip was elected by God his proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
<pb facs="tcp:19465:6"/> Biſhoppe of this Dioceſſe. Whereupon, not hauing determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to whome I might dedicate this worke, I reſolued with my ſelfe to offer it to your Lordeſhippe, as a preſent, wherewith God hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled mee beeyng one of your dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, to bidde you welcome into our cuntrey. I doubt not, but as it hath pleaſed GOD to make you among vs the chiefe patrone of his cauſe, ſo will you vouchſafe fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably to accept theſe my labours tending onely to the aduauncement of the ſame. GOD long preſerue your Lordeſhippe in good health, increaſe his gracious giftes in you, and of his infinite mercie ſo aſſiſte you with his holy ſpirite, that you may carefully looke vnto vs your flocke, and proſperouſlie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede in all your good doynges, to
<pb facs="tcp:19465:6"/> our comforte, and to his glorie. From mine houſe in Bilſton the fourth of Iune. 1581.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhippes at com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement Iohn Tomkys.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="Matthew" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:19465:7"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19465:7"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>The Summe of the <hi>Goſpell by Saint Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>ATTHEW</hi> ſetteth forth in the firſt chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the kinred and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentage of Chriſt the Lord,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The firſt chapter.</hi> From the firſt verſe vnto the 18.</note> 
               <hi>ſhewing</hi> of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded true man after the fleſh &amp; according to the oracles of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes.<note n="b" place="margin">From the 18. verſe vnto the end of the chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</note> Vnto <hi>the declaration of</hi> his ſtocke he ioyneth his concepcion and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitie, prouing that Chriſt the Lord was purely conceiued of the holy Ghoſt, and not of the ſeede of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> and borne of the pure Virgine <hi>Marie.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">The ſecond chapter.</note> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">The ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me of the whole chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</note> Then hee ſheweth that this Chriſt was borne for the Iewes and the Gentiles: and that the Iewes care not much for Chriſt, but the Gentiles diligently ſeeke him, finde him, and worſhippe him.<note n="d" place="margin">From the 1. verſe to the 3.</note> For God, to declare by ſome famous appearaunce and notable ſhewe this myſtery of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion giuen to the worlde, immediately af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:19465:8"/> the incarnation of the Lorde ſtirreth vp Eaſterne men, euen the<note n="*" place="margin">The great learned and wiſe men amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the Perſians were called <hi>Magi.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Magies,</hi> that is to ſaye chiefe and wiſe men, who iourneying from the Eaſt by the prouocation of a ſtarre, come to Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem to ſeeks the king and redeemer of the worlde, where when as by their plaine reporte it was made know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, that the <hi>Meſſias</hi> the king of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el was borne,<note n="e" place="margin">In the 3. ver.</note> king <hi>Herode</hi> beeyng a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraide<note n="f" place="margin">In the 4. ver.</note> calleth together all the wiſe men of the Iewes, and commaundeth them to ſearche diligentlye the oracles of the Prophetes touching the birth and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie of the <hi>Meſſias.</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">From the giver. vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 8.</note> They aunſwere foorthwith that the captayne of Iſrael ſhoulde be borne in Bethlehem <hi>a citie</hi> of Iurie.<note n="h" place="margin">From the 8. ver. vnto the 11</note> Therefore the wiſe men take their iourney to Bethlehem,<note n="i" place="margin">In the 11. ve.</note> where they finde the Lorde his<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Maſshiah</hi> in Hebrue, is as much to ſay as Annoynted in Engliſh.</note> 
               <hi>Meſſias</hi> very poore and of ſmall reputation, yet, doe they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly worſhip him, &amp; honour him with myſticall preſentes, and witneſſe by this their deede, firſt that this child, although he ſeeme to be of contemptible conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is the Lorde of all men, and the king and
<pb facs="tcp:19465:8"/> deliuerer both of the Iewes &amp; Gentiles: ſecondly that the ſame ought to bee woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped and honoured of all men.<note n="k" place="margin">From the 16. ver. vnto the 19</note> The meane ſeaſon that olde ſerpent <hi>the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill</hi> practiſeth his ancient artes. For hee ſtirreth vp <hi>Herode</hi> the king of the Iewes, to deſtroye Chriſt the true king of Iſrael in the beginning of his grouth. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the cruell and ambitious tyrant through crueltie not hearde of <hi>before</hi> fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the coaſtes of Bethlehem with the moſt innocent blood of infantes, if by chaunce in this ſlaughter of infantes, bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng two yeeres olde or vnder, hee might deſtroye the king of Iſrael alſo:<note n="l" place="margin">From the 12. ver. vnto the 16</note> but this abhominable and wicked hope decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued that moſte vile and filthye wretche. For the Lord is conueyed by the counſell of the Angell of the Lorde into Egypt,<note n="m" place="margin">From the 19 ver. vnto the end of the chapter.</note> where hee laye hidde vntill the ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance of GOD had deſtroyed that wicked murtherer.<note n="n" place="margin">The myſticall ſenſe of the 2. Chapter.</note> whiche thinges were forewarning tokens of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Chriſt, and of the affaires to come of the Church, wherin Chriſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> only ſaluation, the appoynted king ouer
<pb facs="tcp:19465:9"/> all the worlde, is alway aſſaulted of the wicked, and yet doeth hee the meane while woorke the ſaluation of the fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and by ſuffering continually ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teineth the victorie: and yet ſo, that the Godlye notwithſtanding are exerciſed with continuall temptations and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions to their owne profite and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye.<note n="o" place="margin">A briefe argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the third and fourth chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</note> The third and fourth Chapter ſette forth vnto thee, reader, a clearer and plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner manifeſtation of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſte the Sauiour of the worlde. For the Father doth not now ſhew his Sonne to a fewe and to certayne choſen <hi>for the purpoſe,</hi> or by one or two reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as hetherto wee ſawe hee did: but made him knowen to all the worlde, and that by innumerable and moſte euident demonſtrations and proofes, and propoſed him to bee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden moſt manifeſtlye with all his trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures.<note place="margin">The 3. chap.</note> 
               <note n="p" place="margin">From the firſt verſe vnto the thirtienth.</note> For firſt hee calleth foorth <hi>Iohn</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Zacharie</hi> the prieſt, the verye <hi>Helias</hi> promiſed in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes, a man of moſt holye life, and of verye greate authoritie emong the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb facs="tcp:19465:9"/> of the Iewes, and maketh him his meſſenger to preache the comming of his ſonne into the fleſhe, and too pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the mindes of all men, that they might bee the more readye to receiue Chriſt, when hee came. Therefore this <hi>Helias (Iohn the Baptiſt)</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth forth, and exhorteth all men to repentaunce, and to prepare them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues for the Lord againſt his comming.<note n="*" place="margin">In the 2. chap.</note> For he addeth expreſſely, that the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen is at hande,<note n="i" place="margin">What is mea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t by the kingdome of heauen.</note> that is to ſaye, that that time approched, yea was preſent, wherein GOD by his Prophetes had promiſed, that hee woulde powre foorth by his Sonne all the treaſures of his grace and giftes vppon men, and that hee woulde raigne in them.<note n="*" place="margin">In the 6. ver.</note> Vnto this doctrine hee addeth the famous and holy Sacrament of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, whereby hee might repreſent e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen viſibly the myſteries of GOD, to the woorſhippers of GOD, and gea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther together into one bodye the faithfull people, and graffe them into Chriſt.<note n="q" place="margin">In the verſe.</note> And then the heauenly father calleth forth
<pb facs="tcp:19465:10"/> alſo his own ſonne forth of Galilee, where he lay hidde hitherto, into Iurie, that, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the mindes of the common people ſeemed now ſufficiently prepared by the baptiſt to receiue Chriſt, he himſelf might come foorth in open view now, declaring &amp; ſhewing himſelf to the world no longer by the teſtimonie of others, but by his own doctrine, and by his owne vertues. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lorde commeth into Iurie vnto Iordane, where Iohn taught and baptiſed into Chriſte, and hee alſo is baptiſed of <hi>Iohn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="r" place="margin">In the 14. &amp; 15. verſe.</note>Moreouer the Baptiſt acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth forthwith the Sauiour of the world, and therefore witneſſeth in moſt manifeſt woordes, that this verie ſelfe ſame is the Sonne of GOD, the lambe of GOD, whiche ſhoulde take awaye the ſinnes of the worlde, of whom hitherto hee ſpake, for whom hee commaunded all men to wayte, and now repeating the very ſelfe ſame thing feruently, he ſendeth all men to Chriſt onely.<note n="ſ" place="margin">In the 16. ve.</note> Furthermore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly father addeth hereunto from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen his honourable and ſtrange witneſſe.
<pb facs="tcp:19465:10"/> For after that the heauens were opened, and <hi>the holy Ghoſt</hi> was lighted vppon the head of Chriſte in the viſible likeneſſe of an heauenly doue, hee ſaieth, as it were poynting foorth his finger toward Chriſt,<note n="t" place="margin">In the 17. ve.</note> and alſo adding thereunto a moſt cleere voyce, <hi>This is my dearelie beloued So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne,</hi> yea and ſo thorowly beloued, that for his ſake onely, I am nowe thorowly pleaſed and reconciled to the worlde, wherewith for their ſinnes I was moſte greeuouſly offended.<note n="*" place="margin">The 4. chap.</note> 
               <note n="v" place="margin">From the 1. ver. vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 12.</note> And hee, after ſo excellent a teſtimonie did not foorthwith preache him ſelfe, and ſette foorth himſelfe to bee beholden and inioyed of all men, but entering into the barries, or wreaſtling place of moſt ſtrong temptations, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>Adam</hi> fighting vnhappely was ſubdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, hee nowe the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending more happelye, both conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth Satan the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>querour, and taught vs alſo to conquere him being conquered:<note n="x" place="margin">From the 12 ver. vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 18.</note> and nowe beyng conquerour, commeth foorth at the laſt with greate authoritye, as the Lorde of the Deuill, and
<pb facs="tcp:19465:11"/> of all thinges, and promiſeth his woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers life, and euerye good thing, yea and the kingdome of heauen alſo, preaching the grace of GOD, and the forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, and exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting all men to the amendement of lyfe.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="y" place="margin">From the 18. verſe vnto the 23.</note>Furthermore that wee might vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande, that this promiſing of life, and preaching of grace doeth not onelye pertayne to the men of that age, but alſo vnto all men, whiche ſhoulde come after, euen to the ende of the world, hee chooſeth to him ſelfe Diſciples, whom hee might appoynt witneſſes in the worlde of all thinges, which he ſpake and did, and whom hee might thorowely teache the myſterye of lyfe, that they beeyng perfectlye inſtructed, might commende bothe by liuely voyce and by writinges liuing for euer, the treaſures of the grace of God, beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed through Chriſte vppon all the worlde and in all ages, and that they might as it were diſtribute <hi>the ſame.</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">From the 23. verſe to the end of the chapter.</note> He addeth heereunto notable and greate benefites, in curing by his vertue and
<pb facs="tcp:19465:11"/> power all diſeaſes, although vncura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.<note n="a" place="margin">The vſe of the Miracles of Chriſt.</note> For ſo doeth hee declare vnto vs all, not onelye in woordes, but alſo euen by his vertue and power, that hee is euen ſuche, as his doctrine ſetteth him foorth, that is to ſay, the Sauiour of the worlde, whiche both is willing and able to ſaue them whiche woorſhippe him: and therefore they alſo ought to committe themſelues by fayth to him onelye.<note n="b" place="margin">A briefe reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of the con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tentes of theſe two chapters before going.</note> Theſe bee the holye and wholeſome <hi>documentes,</hi> whiche thou learneſt in theſe two chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, ſo that the verye maieſtie and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite of ſo greate a matter may cauſe thee to bee ſtudious and diligent, except thou bee altogether a ſtocke.<note n="c" place="margin">A briefe repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition of the fourth chapter.</note> Emong other thinges, whiche <hi>Matthewe</hi> hath ſette foorth vnto vs in this fourth chapter <hi>before goyng</hi> hee hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs a certaine taſte of the ſermons of the doctrine of Chriſte touching repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, and forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, that is to ſaye, of the myſterye of the Goſpell and grace of GOD, I meane of the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging and confeſſing of our
<pb facs="tcp:19465:12"/> ſinnes, and of the turning from our ſinnes to the liuing GOD, through the faith of Ieſus Chriſt, whereby wee ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne remiſſion of our ſinnes and euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting life, ſo many of vs as beleeue with all our heartes:<note n="d" place="margin">A briefe argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the 5.6 and 7. chapters.</note> nowe the ſame Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour <hi>Matthewe</hi> goeth forwarde and expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth in the three chapters folowing other chiefe places alſo of the doctrine of Chriſt, not vſing now his accuſtomed briefeneſſe, that is to ſay, regeſtring on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ſumme of the Lorde his talke, but ſetting foorth at large, Chriſte his whole ſermon, euen as it was made by himſelfe, that wee might thereby iudge more certainely and rightly of all the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of Chriſt, and that after repentance and remiſſion of ſinnes, beeing two chiefe pointes of our religion, wee might alſo more fully vnderſtande other verye excellent places of Chriſtian religion.<note n="e" place="margin">The qualitie of Chriſt his Sermon.</note> The oration or ſermon of Chriſte is ſpent in teaching and expounding, and in ſome places alſo in giuing of preceptes, beeyng therefore diuers and made of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers matters.<note n="*" place="margin">The 5 chap.</note> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">From the 1. ver. vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 17.</note> For firſt hee diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
<pb facs="tcp:19465:12"/> plainely of the true bleſſedneſſe or happineſſe, ſhewing in what thinges it doth conſiſt, and in the meane ſeaſon priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confuting the fooliſhe and corrupt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions of the common people touching the true felicitie.<note n="g" place="margin">From the 17. ver. vnto the end of the chapter.</note> Then hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to purge the lawe. For the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees had corrupted it with their traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and made it obſcure with their falſe expoſitions. Therefore hee ſheweth manifeſtly by certayne examples taken foorth of the lawe, whiche is the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſenſe of the lawe, and what the lawe of GOD requireth of vs, ſetting foorth with all the difference of true and counterfaite righteouſneſſe.<note n="*" place="margin">The 6. chap.</note> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">A briefe ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt part of the 6. chap. From y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 1. ver. vnto the 19</note> And becauſe hee reaſoned of righteouſneſſe, and emonge all the woorkes of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe the moſte excellent are almes, or mercifulneſſe, or bountifulneſſe, alſo prayer or a feruent talking with God, and faſting, or the chaſtiſing of the bodye, and of our fleſhe, therefore our Lorde pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth theſe woorkes of righteouſneſſe, or exerciſes of godlineſſe, from hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, wherewith the Phariſees had polluted them, reſtoring them to
<pb facs="tcp:19465:13"/> their auncient and naturall beautie,<note n="i" place="margin">From the firſt verſe vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 5.</note> and ſhewing moſte woorthily howe wee ſhoulde geue our almes aright,<note n="k" place="margin">From the 5. verſe vnto the 16.</note> howe wee ſhoulde praye truelye,<note n="l" place="margin">From the 16. verſe vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 19</note> and howe wee ſhoulde faſt religiouſly.<note n="m" place="margin">A briefe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe againſt co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſnes in the end of the chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</note> Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vppon forſomuche as it is moſte mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, that none other affection doeth ſo greatelye withdrawe vs from all god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe and righteouſneſſe, as the deſire of hauing, and the ouermuche curious carefulneſſe for meate, drynke, and cloth, <hi>and other thinges needefull.</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">From the 19 verſe vnto the end of the chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</note> Therefore in the fourth place hee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwadeth vs by his graue ſpeache from couetouſneſſe, and plucketh vp aptlye ouermuche carefulneſſe, that is to ſaie, wicked miſtruſt, foorth of the heartes of his <hi>ſeruauntes,</hi> and ingraffeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne fayth towardes GOD, and a faithfull deſire of religion and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe.<note n="*" place="margin">The ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>th chapter.</note>
               <note n="o" place="margin">From the 1. verſe vnto the 7.</note> Afterwardes ſignifiyng with greate faithfulneſſe and diligence, that the raſhe iudgement of men touching other men, I meane backebyting and ſclaundering, ought to bee auoyded, he teacheth vs to vſe our tongue moderate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:19465:13"/> and rightly. For there ſpringeth no leſſe troubles foorth of the abuſe of the tongue, than foorth of couetouſneſſe and the deſire of hauing.<note n="p" place="margin">From the 7 verſe vnto the 12.</note> Moreouer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all theſe thinges are made perfect in vs by diuine vertue through the benefite of grace, not through our owne ſtrength, therefore the Lorde doeth exhorte, profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly and in place, his worſhippers to faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full prayers, whereby they maye craue, that ſtrength may be giuen them of God, leaſt at any time they faint in doing their dutie. Beſides this he maketh moſt cleare and moſt large promiſes, promiſing that hee will heare the prayers of the faithfull, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> therby he may the more kindle &amp; inflame in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> godly the deſire to pray.<note n="q" place="margin">In the 12. verſe.</note> And draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into a briefe ſumme all theſe thinges hitherto moſt ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tifully propoſed, he ſaith: <hi>All things, whatſoeuer ye would that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould doe to you, do ye euen ſo to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for this is the law &amp; the Prophets</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">In the 13. &amp; 14. verſes.</note> The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> propoſing two wayes, and ſhewing the manner, the reaſon, and the end of both the wayes, hee exhorteth vs all to enter into that way, which indeede is the ſtraighter
<pb facs="tcp:19465:14"/> and rougher, but yet leadeth vs in vnto life euerlaſting.<note n="ſ" place="margin">From the 15. verſe vnto the 21.</note> Againe becauſe hee had ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the way, through the which men goe to deſtruction, hee giueth diligent warding foorthwith, leaſt any where the godly ſhoulde bee ledde out of the way to their deſtruction, by the practiſes and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiptfulneſſe of falſe Prophetes, whom he paynteth foorth in their colours, leaſt they ſhould deceiue the ſimple with their goodlie ſhewe, and leaſt the godly ſhould be plucked from the way of truth into the incumbrances of hereſies, and vnto their vtter ruine.<note n="t" place="margin">From the 21. verſ. vnto the 24.</note> At the laſt concluding this moſt diuine ſermon, he ſheweth plainelye in the laſt place, that none outward ſhew doth profite any man to the making per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of godlineſſe,<note n="v" place="margin">From the 24. verſe vnto the end of the chap.</note> therefore <hi>hee gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vs to vnderſtande</hi> that it is not ſufficient for the obtayning of godlineſſe and <hi>euerlaſting</hi> life, to heare and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande the worde of GOD, or to bragge with loftie woordes, except wee expreſſe <hi>the ſame</hi> alſo by the moſt holy woorkes of faith and vertues: and this doeth hee declare by a feyned narration or a verye
<pb facs="tcp:19465:14"/> proper parable, and ſetteth it foorth before all mens eyes, exhorting euerye one of vs to the true ſtudie of true god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, whiche hath the continuing and moſte ſweete fruite of <hi>euerlaſting</hi> life.<note n="x" place="margin">The concluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the expoſition of the ſermon.</note> And this is the argument and ſumme of all the oration, whiche our Lorde and ſauiour Chriſte made to all people in the mountaine. Thereof Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith: <hi>It appeareth that this ſermon conteyneth perfectlye all thoſe preceptes wherewith Chriſtian life is inſtructed.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſtine.</note>
               <note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Matthevv</hi> his purpoſe in the 3. chap. laſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore goyng.</note> 
               <hi>Matthewe</hi> hath reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the three chapters before goyng the whole ſermon of Chriſte, that hee might geue vs a taſte, and as it were geather together the ſumme of all the doctrine of Chriſte,<note n="z" place="margin">His purpoſe in the 2. chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters folowing.</note> and in theſe two chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters following hee ſetteth foorth plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye the vertue and the exceeding great power of Chriſte, by geathering to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether verye many his myraculous be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites, and propoſeth the ſame <hi>pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> beeyng ſo ſette foorth to bee dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentlye conſidered of all men<note n="a" place="margin">The vſe of the miracles of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</note> that thereby all the worlde maye geather that
<pb facs="tcp:19465:15"/> Ieſus Chriſte is the liuing, true, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty ſonne, of the liuing and almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie GOD: and that hee is not onely al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, but that hee is alſo moſt bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, whiche came to conuert, to heale, and to ſaue ſinners. This doth he proue, I ſay, moſt euidently by the moſt diuine and moſt ſtrange miracles wrought by Chriſt, whereof this is the ſumme.<note n="*" place="margin">The eight chapter.</note> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">From the 1. verſe vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 5.</note> Firſt he cleanſeth the Leper, which made ſute vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him.<note n="c" place="margin">From the 5. verſe vnto the 14.</note> Then he reſtoreth to life and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect health a certayne Centurion his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt, beeyng readie to giue vp the Ghoſt foorthwith, and as it were dead.<note n="d" place="margin">In the 14. &amp; 15. verſe.</note> After this hee healeth Saint <hi>Peter</hi> his wiues mother lying ſicke of a feuer:<note n="e" place="margin">From the 16. verſe vnto the 19.</note> and to bee briefe cuteth all the infirmities of all.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="f" place="margin">From the 23. verſe vnto the 28.</note>Moreouer rebuking the very Sea, beyng a moſt barbarous Element, and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging with cruel tempeſts, he made it more calme than any oyle.<note n="g" place="margin">From the 28. verſe vnto the end of the chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</note> Straight way af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he draweth vnto him by his hid vertue, two poſſeſſed with Deuils, who breaking into peeces all their boltes and chaines, were verye troubleſome to paſſengers,
<pb facs="tcp:19465:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> and could not be kept in order by the ſkill or ſtrength of any, foorth of theſe miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>creatures</hi> hee caſteth a whole legion <hi>of diuels</hi> and reſtoreth them to their firſt health.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">The 9. chap.</note> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">From the 1. ver. vnto the 9.</note>Furthermore, hee ſo deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from a moſt greeuous diſeaſe, a man ſicke of a palſie lying in a bedde, not a man, but more truly y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miſerable carkaſſe of a man, that foorthwith hee ſtanding on his feete walked luſtily, which hetherto was borne of others, and to make ſhorte, he him ſelfe bare his bed ſtronglie on his ſhoulders, whereby whileſt he was ſicke he was ſtaied vp.<note n="i" place="margin">In the 9. ver.</note> And then is <hi>Leui (o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe called Matthew)</hi> called to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance,<note n="k" place="margin">From the 10. ver. vnto the 14</note> and alſo a great hope is ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto ſinners, which turne to Chriſte.<note n="l" place="margin">From the 20. ver. vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 23.</note> After theſe things were thus done, the incurable diſeaſe of the woman, which was pittifully diſeaſed with an iſſue of blood, is cured.<note n="m" place="margin">In the 18. &amp; 19. ver. &amp; from the 23. ver<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the 27.</note> Alſo <hi>Iairus</hi> his daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which was dead, is called back to life.<note n="n" place="margin">From the 27 ver. vnto the 32</note> And two blinde men receiue their ſight,<note n="o" place="margin">From the 32. ver. vnto the 35.</note> and a certaine man in very miſerable plight is deliuered from a dumbe Diuel.<note n="p" place="margin">In the 35 ver.</note> Neither wrought he theſe few myracles
<pb facs="tcp:19465:16"/> only, but going through all cities and vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lages, and preaching the Goſpell of the kingdome, he healed all ſickneſſes and all diſeaſes among the people.<note n="q" place="margin">what we muſt learne by theſe myracles.</note> By all theſe <hi>myracles Matthew</hi> the apoſtle declareth vnto vs, &amp; proueth as it were by moſt ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g &amp; vnrefutable arguments &amp; teſtimonies, that Chriſte is the true ſonne of the true God, the Lorde of all thinges, I meane of all elements, of all diſeaſes and afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, of all ſinnes, of the Diuell, and of death it ſelfe: and that therefore hee came into this worlde, that hee might make vs the Lordes of all thinges, and the ſonnes of God, namely if wee receiue him with true faith.<note n="r" place="margin">The maner of Matthew his writing.</note> Therefore <hi>Matthew</hi> his purpoſe is, not only to deſcribe by the deedes <hi>of Chriſt,</hi> the vertue of Chriſt, and that he is the bountifull and liberall beſtower of all good things, but alſo to paint foorth their faith and all their maners which receiued the benefites of Chriſt.<note n="ſ" place="margin">What wee muſt learne of them, vpon who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt wrought his myracles.</note> For of them, as of liuely examples, we learn what maner of faith ours ought to bee, and howe wee ſhould behaue our ſelues; that we may be made partakers of the benefites of God, that is to ſay, howe wee may become the
<pb facs="tcp:19465:16"/> ſonnes of God, and the Lordes of thinges, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neither ſinne, nor death, nor the diuel himſelfe can hurt, if wee following their examples, doe thoſe thinges, which they did.<note n="t" place="margin">Certaine points omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted purpoſely in the narration before going.</note> Now he intermedleth among theſe <hi>myracles</hi> certaine things in the <hi>8.</hi> Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter touching the<note n="v" place="margin">In the 8 chap. the 11. and 12. ver. &amp; the 19.20.22. &amp; 22. verſe.</note> calling to the faith of the Goſpell, and in the 9. chapter concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning<note n="x" place="margin">In the 9. cha. From the 14. vnto the 18 ver.</note> faſting, and certaine other things, which alſo make to the ſetting foorth of the vertue of faith, and of the power and gentleneſſe of the Lord.<note n="y" place="margin">The deedes and words of Chriſt.</note> And it is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry euident and familiar kinde of doctrine to teach by hiſtorie or examples, that is to ſay, rather by deedes then by wordes: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the three firſt Euangeliſtes doe more often handle the doings <hi>of Chriſt</hi> then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare his ſayings. And in deede Chriſte ſeemeth vnto vs to bee much more liuely, when he worketh <hi>myracles</hi> than when he teacheth. For although his doctrine had a diuine efficacie and force alſo, yet do his deedes after a ſort excel, exerciſing and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouing that which is taught. Let no man therfore contemne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> former Euangeliſtes in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſon of <hi>Iohn,</hi> becauſe he ſeemeth to be more often occupied &amp;. more dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t
<pb facs="tcp:19465:17"/> in opening the wordes of Chriſt: whoſe wordes alſo haue their maieſtie: for the holy Ghoſt hath directed the mindes and pennes of all <hi>the Euangeliſts</hi> to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that wee might haue, foorth of foure authours of ſufficient credite, a moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine &amp; vndoubted hiſtorie of al the words and deedes of Chriſt.<note n="z" place="margin">What order Matthew vſeth</note> It appeareth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo by thoſe thinges, which haue beene han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deled hitherto, that <hi>Matthew</hi> in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vſed a naturall order, and ſomewhat after an artificial, &amp; that he goeth forward now chiefly in this order, becauſe it is moſt fitte to teach by. For he ſeemeth to haue a care, not ſo much to ſet foorth faithfully that which was ſaid &amp; done by the Lorde, as to place euery thing in his owne place and order, and fitly to teach by fitte order, and chiefly to moue the mindes of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, yea and to ingraffe moſte deepely Chriſt, and faith in Chriſt.<note n="a" place="margin">A briefe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſall of thoſe thinges whiche Matthew hath ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dled hitherto.</note> Hitherto <hi>Matthew</hi> hath reported a certain abridge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctrine of Chriſt the Lord, wherby he plentifully inſtructed his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers in true godlineſſe: heerevnto he hath ioyned certaine of his greateſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, euen diuine and wonderfull
<pb facs="tcp:19465:17"/> workes, whereby he hath declared that he is the mightie and gentle Lorde of all things, which can make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo, that ſtick vnto him by true faith, Lordes of ſinne, of death, of Satan, and of all things els. In this buſineſſe hee had choſen to himſelfe witneſſes, whom hitherto he made both be holders and hearers of all his <hi>matters,</hi> as well of his ſayings, as of his doings: to this ende verily, that they might after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes bring foorth into all the world the charge of common ſaluation, now concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued &amp; laid vp in their mindes.<note n="b" place="margin">From the 36. ver. vnto the end of the chapter.</note> And now they ſeemed ſufficiently inſtructed in the rudiments and principles of faith and of Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, therfore it was conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhold be furder exerciſed therin, and by the meanes thereof prepared to greater matters:<note n="*" place="margin">The 10. chap.</note>
               <note n="c" place="margin">From the 1. ver. vnto the 7.</note> and therefore they are ſent foorth of the Lorde him ſelfe to preach the Goſpell now to the people of Iſrael only,<note n="d" place="margin">From the 7. ver. vnto the 16</note> and are inſtructed in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine commandements. For the Lord doth dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly preſcribe what they ought to do, &amp; what their office is:<note n="e" place="margin">In the 16.17 &amp; 18. verſes.</note> And he ſheweth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo what they ſhall ſuffer, yea how pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilous a thing it is to be a miniſter of the
<pb facs="tcp:19465:18"/> worde in a corrupt &amp; vnthankfull age.<note n="f" place="margin">From the 19. verſe vnto the end of the chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</note> Therefore he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forteth his <hi>diſciples</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily &amp; finely with furniſhed talk, teaching them how they ought to continue conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in all aduerſities in true godlines, &amp; to ouercome all euils.<note n="*" place="margin">The 11. cha.</note> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">In the 1. ver.</note> Afterward <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi> ſheweth, how the Lorde Ieſus him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, who only is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended &amp; inioyned to the true preachers of God his worde to be preached by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, diſcloſed himſelf, &amp; made himſelfe knowne to be the true <hi>Mesſias,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> only expected ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the world: which verily is the firſt &amp; moſt ſure foundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of all the Lord his preaching.<note n="h" place="margin">From the 2. ver. vnto the 16</note> In the ſame place alſo is ſet foorth the prayſe of <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> that is to ſay a moſt cleere exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of a very good miniſter, propoſed to al thoſe, which are deſirous to doe their duty aright.<note n="i" place="margin">From the 16. ver. vnto the 25</note> And foorthwith is adioyned an excellent exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of a ſermon of the Lord. Firſt, how he rebuked the ſtubborne vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe of his own nation, &amp; left a paterne of accuſation &amp; reproofe to his miniſters.<note n="k" place="margin">In the 25. &amp; 26. ver.</note> Then how he preached the kingdome of God to men of a better hope.<note n="l" place="margin">In the 27. ver</note> He ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that he hath the power of all things, &amp; that hee is the fountaine of all goodneſſe, which ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not bee drawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> drie, which is wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb facs="tcp:19465:18"/> &amp; deſirous to be drawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note n="m" place="margin">In the 28.29. &amp; 30. ver.</note> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he inuiteth all men vnto him, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth to graunt reſt vnto all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in what diſtreſſe ſo euer they be.<note n="*" place="margin">The 12. cha.</note>
               <note n="n" place="margin">From the 1. verſe vnto the 9.</note> Then doth hee diligently handle the queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous keping of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sabboth, &amp; admoniſhing by the way y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tifulnes and the inwarde worſhipping of God, is more allowed of God, than the outwarde keeping of <hi>the Saboth.</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">From the 9. verſe to the 14.</note> Moreouer y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> bountifulnes, which lately he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended, he ſheweth to a certaine miſerable ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> very greatly afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a withered ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, which he reſtored to him ſound.<note n="p" place="margin">From the 14. verſe vnto the 22.</note> And becauſe he could ſoften the hardnes of the people of the <hi>Iewes</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by any benefits, nor by any myracles, forſomuch as they did ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>times co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpire a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, he departeth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for a time, practiſing nothing more bitter or more ſharpe againſt them, if peraduenture they might be ouercome with gentlenes &amp; lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſuffering, preſcribing by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very ſame deed of his a forme to his miniſters, what they ſhould do alſo in the like caſes and w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuch maner of men. But hee ſhrinketh not from his office, hee leaueth not off to doe good, neither forſaketh hee the <hi>vndertaken</hi> defence of the trueth, yeeldyng no
<pb facs="tcp:19465:19"/> whit at all in theſe points to his enemies.<note n="q" place="margin">In the 22. &amp; 23. verſes.</note> Therefore he deliuereth from the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell one poſſeſſed with a Deuill, which was brought vnto him, being blinde and dumbe, &amp; reſtoreth vnto him the vſe of his tongue and of his eyes:<note n="r" place="margin">In the 24. verſe.</note> and becauſe the Phariſees did detract this diuine deed, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribing it to the working by the Diuell,<note n="ſ" place="margin">From the 25. ver. vnto the 30</note> the Lord taketh vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him the defence of the truth, &amp; proueth by moſt ſtrong argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his myracles, workes, yea and all his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings were wrought by the power of God &amp; not of the Diuell, and that therefore the kingdome of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was now come. And here doth he againe moſt plainely ſet forth that, which lately wee ſaid was the chiefe point of our religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, namely, that Ieſus is Chriſt.<note n="t" place="margin">Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the 30. ver. vnto the 46</note> And foorthwith ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deling his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries, as they deſerued, hee rebuketh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> moſt grauely. For he ſheweth at large their want of belief, or rather their vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines, &amp; declareth what ſhall become of the conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ners of the kingdom of God.<note n="v" place="margin">From the 46 ver. vnto the end of the Chapter.</note> Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he putteth backe his mother &amp; his cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſins, which were deſirous to ſpeake with him, by a ſomewhat hard anſwere, ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therby, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the leaſt muſt not be yelded to carnall affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, ſo oft as the affaires of
<pb facs="tcp:19465:19"/> the kingdome of God are in handeling.<note n="x" place="margin">A briefe repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition of the 3. chapters laſt before going.</note> In the three chapters laſt before going, Matthew hath intreated of the Miniſters of God his worde, and of certaine chiefe pointes of our religion:<note n="y" place="margin">The matter bandeled in the 2. chapters fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</note> and nowe doeth there followe a more plentifull treatiſe of the woorde of GOD, of the vertue, fruite, and price thereof: which is fitly knitte to the matter before going. For the miniſterie of the worde of God is occupied in the verie word of God. And this treatiſe is ſet foorth in parabolicall ſpeaches and ſimilitudes, that at the leaſt by this meanes the mindes of the godly might be ſtirred vp to the ſearching forth of the trueth and myſteries of God.<note n="*" place="margin">The 13. cha.</note> 
               <note n="z" place="margin">From the firſt verſ. vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 24.</note> And the firſt parable, propoſed touching him which ſowed ſeede in the fielde, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that there be diuers kindes of hearers of God his worde, and that God doth not allowe all the hearers of his worde, but them onely, in whom the ſeede proſpereth vntill it bring forth due fruite.<note n="a" place="margin">From the 24 verſ. vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 31.</note> Forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with by an other parable, that is to ſay by the ſimilitude of the tares, hee pointeth forth as it were with the finger an other fault alſo and plague of tilled land, teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the meane ſeaſon, howe good ſeede
<pb facs="tcp:19465:20"/> may be preſerued ſounde.<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <p>In the 31.32 &amp;. 33. verſes. In the 34. and 35. verſes is ſhewed the cauſe why Ieſus ſpake by ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes.</p>
                  <p>From the 36 vnto the 44. verſe chriſt repoundeth the parable of the tares.</p>
               </note> After this by two other ſimilitudes, taken from the graine of muſtarde ſeede and from leuen, hee ſheweth howe great the power of the worde of God is, and howe euidently it worketh in them by whome it is receiued, although it ſeeme to the worlde vile and contemned.<note n="c" place="margin">In the 44, 45 and 46. verſes.</note> In the fourth place by two other ſimilituds, propoſed touching a treaſure <hi>hidde</hi> in the fielde, and a moſt precious pearle, he ſignifieth that the price of God his worde is ſo great, that in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon hereof we ought to contemne all thinges in the worlde, although they bee neuer ſo precious, yea that we ought, with the very loſſe of all our goodes, to prouide vs the worde of God.<note n="d" place="margin">From the 47 verſe vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 51</note> Againe in ſetting forth the ſimilitude of the net caſt into the ſea, he ſheweth plainely what ſhal become of them eſpecially, which intermedle them ſelues in the aſſembly of the godly, and yet are hypocrites and counterfeite godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, teaching the meane while that wee muſt not lightly condemn any forthwith, but leaue euery one to his owne iudge.<note n="e" place="margin">In the 51 and 52. verſes.</note> When as he had ſet foorth theſe things after this maner, he commaundeth his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters
<pb facs="tcp:19465:20"/> alſo diligently to way the ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, and for the playner ſetting forth of the trueth, and of the glorie of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of GOD, and for the profite of the Churche, to vſe all the kindes of elocution and apt ſpeach.<note n="f" place="margin">From the 53. verſe vnto the end of the chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</note> And although the Lord taught in ſuch ſort, that no man was able to accuſe either his faithful dealing or his diligence, yet was he litle regarded and accepted of his cuntrey men, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned and laughed to ſcorne the heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doctrine of godlineſſe. But he bare this with a valient minde, giuing an example to all his <hi>miniſters,</hi> that they may alſo take the matter paciently, if the world alſo litle regard them.<note n="*" place="margin">The 14. cap</note> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">From the firſt verſe vnto the 13</note> And then doth <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thewe</hi> forthwith ſette foorth the wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full example of that very good man <hi>Iohn the Baptiſt,</hi> who alſo was very euill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded of Herode for his faithful ſeruice, being moſt pitifully beheaded of him.<note n="h" place="margin">From the 13 verſe vnto the 22.</note> After this he fed in the wilderneſſe by his diuine power a great multitude of men, which w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> merueylous feruentnes thirſted the preaching of the word: ſhewing by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miracle, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the faithful folowers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word
<pb facs="tcp:19465:21"/> of God ſhall want nothing at any time, eſpecially of thoſe thinges whiche are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie and not ſuperfluous. And by the ſame fact he taught his diſciples to helpe the faithfull people hauing neede.<note n="i" place="margin">Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the 22. verſe vnto the ende of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chap.</note> Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he deliuereth his diſciples, which were in perill of the ſtormes of the ſea and of a great tempeſt, and whiche looked for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing els but moſt preſent death: decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſo vnto his, that hee is hee, which can deliuer all from all perils, and can ſaue al men by his power and grace, chiefely the miniſters of his worde. Therefore if the cruell and fearefull example of <hi>Iohn</hi> did any whitte terrifie them, theſe two great and goodly benefites of God do confirme and comfort them againe.<note n="*" place="margin">The 15. cha.</note>
               <note n="k" place="margin">From the 1. ver. vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 21.</note> Vnto the treatiſe of the word of God is fitly ioyned by <hi>Matthewe</hi> the diſputation touching the traditions of men, or the ordinances and conſtitutions of Fathers, as contrary to the worde of God. Chriſt teacheth vs manifeſtly to contemne them, if they tend to the contumelie, derogation, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of God his worde. And becauſe the Phariſees the patrons and defenders of mens traditions, were offended at this
<pb facs="tcp:19465:21"/> wholeſome doctrine of the Lord, the Lord ſheweth foorthwith, that no accomptes at all ought to bee made of ſuch kinde of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and of ſuch kinde of men: declaring the meane ſeaſon, that man is not defiled with outwarde thinges, but rather with thoſe euill thinges, which proceede out of the cloſets of the harte.<note n="l" place="margin">From the 21. verſe vnto the 29.</note> After that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing himſelfe from thoſe indurate and vnthankefull men, hee departed into the cuntrey of the Gentiles, where forthwith a woman of <hi>Syropheniſſa being indued</hi> with a moſt ſtrong faith made a moſt ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt requeſt vnto him: in whome there is ſet foorth moſt manifeſtly both a meruey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous example of true faith, and alſo the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect therof. For after the reproofe of falſe doctrine, which is the mother of falſe faith, there is ſet foorth with great diligence in theſe 15, 16, and 17 chapters, as was alſo in the 8, and 9 chapters, true faith in the Lorde, and the true nature of faith, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo <hi>in the ſame</hi> are opened the chiefeſt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of our faith.<note n="m" place="margin">From the 29. verſe vnto the ende of the chapter.</note> Moreouer returning againe into Galilee, he feedeth againe the common people, which followed him, ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing by this benefite alſo, that it is hee,
<pb facs="tcp:19465:22"/> which can feede both the ſoule and the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, and that therefore this foode muſt bee ſought for by faith only and moſt ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hands of the ſhepheard Chriſt.<note n="*" place="margin">The 16. chapter.</note> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">From the firſt verſe vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 5.</note> Afterwardes he repelleth and putteth backe the Phariſees requiring a ſigne, whereby he might proue himſelfe to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Meſſias,</hi> by ſhewing them the ſigne of his death &amp; of his reſurrection:<note n="o" place="margin">From the 5. verſe vnto the 13.</note> then doth he commande his <hi>diſciples</hi> to beware of the doctrine of the Phariſees &amp; Sadduces: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which thing althoug hee had taught in the beginning of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 15. chapt. yet both he here ſpeake of it againe in the 16 chapter, as a matter very neceſſary for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church.<note n="p" place="margin">From the 13. verſe vnto the 21.</note> Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that returning to the commendatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of faith, he layeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> foundation of fayth, buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the Church vpon the foundation, and pointeth forth as it were with the finger, whiche is the true faith of the Catholike Church, &amp; which is the true and right con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, ſhewing alſo howe the ſame may be planted.<note n="q" place="margin">From the 21 verſe vnto the end of the chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</note> Where vnto hee forthwith adioyneth a moſt manifeſt doctrine of his paſſion and reſurrection, alſo of the deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng of one his ſelfe and of the bearing of
<pb facs="tcp:19465:22"/> his croſſe after Chriſt, and of the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to come, that is to ſay, of the greateſt articles of our faith, and of the holy duety of Chriſtians, a doctrine altogether per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayning to the perfectneſſe of faith.<note n="*" place="margin">The 17. chapter.</note>
               <note n="r" place="margin">From the 1. ver. vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 14.</note> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine leaſt any ſhould be offended at this ſorowful doctrine ful of labours &amp; paines touching the bearing of the croſſe, <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thewe</hi> adioyneth here vnto immediatly the glorious tranſformation of Chriſt the Lorde in the mountaine, whereby he part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gaue vs a taſt of what ſort he ſhoulde be in his glorie, and what the maner of the glory to come is, whiche is prepared for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whiche faithfully and paciently beare the croſſe of Chriſt: and partly he ſheweth alſo moſt euidently, that he is very Chriſt promiſed in the lawe and the prophetes, that hee might confirme the faith of all which beleeue in him. And hee propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thoſe thinges ſo manifeſtly to his diſciples, that they did nowe plainely vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande, that Ieſus was Chriſt, and that therfore they did moue the queſtion of the coming of <hi>Helias</hi> the meſſenger of the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> where vnto the Lord anſwering
<pb facs="tcp:19465:23"/> forthwith, affirmed plainely that hee was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Meſſias,</hi> &amp; that <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> was <hi>Helias.</hi>
               <note n="s" place="margin">From the 14 verſe vnto the 19.</note> Laſtly he reſtored a certaine Lunatike man vnto his father, which made ſute for him, declaring againe by the ſame benefit, that he is the king of his people, and the conquerour of the Diuell:<note n="t" place="margin">From the 19 verſe vnto the 22.</note> ſhewing alſo howe great the power of faith is, and howe greate the euill of vnbeleefe is, concluding that by temperance and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinence proceeding from a true faith, the force of the Deuill is chiefely broken.<note n="v" place="margin">In the 22. and 23. verſes</note> And herunto doth he forthwith adioyne the preaching and forſhewing of his death and paſſion, not without great and plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full fruite.<note n="x" place="margin">Wherof Mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thew intreated laſt, and wherof he ſpeaketh next</note> Faith in the Lorde Ieſus beyng well taught, and the true knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the kingdome of the Sonne of God being well obtayned, whereof <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thewe</hi> hath hitherto intreated at large, he paſſeth nowe wiſely to thoſe thinges, which almoſt ſtande in the outwarde con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation of man, and which notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding perteyne to the kingdome of Chriſt.<note n="y" place="margin">From the 24 verſe vnto the ende of the cha.</note> Of the whiche kinde the queſtion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Magiſtrate is: What Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians owe vnto him? The Lorde ſheweth
<pb facs="tcp:19465:23"/> therefore by his owne example, what wee ought to doe herein rightly.<note n="*" place="margin">The 18. cha.</note> 
               <note n="z" place="margin">From the 1. ver. vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 7.</note> Like vnto this is the queſtion touching eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall preheminence: Who ſhould be the greateſt in the kingdome of heauen? Here the Lorde withdraweth the mindes of his <hi>diſciples</hi> from ambition and from the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations rayſed touching the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie and chiefe authoritie, and teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> moſt diligently humilitie.<note n="a" place="margin">From the 7. verſ. vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 15.</note> Then doth he adioyne herevnto a profitable ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition for the auoyding of offence:<note n="b" place="margin">In the 15. and 16. verſes</note> where he intreateth alſo of brotherly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition,<note n="c" place="margin">From the 17. verſe vnto the 21.</note> of reprouing offenders open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and<note n="d" place="margin">From the 21. verſe vnto the ende of the chapter.</note> of forgiuing a treſpaſſe, wherein grauely perſwading all men, hee ſetteth foorth a moſt goodly parable concerning the ſame matter.<note n="*" place="margin">The 19. cha.</note> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">From the firſt verſ. vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 10.</note> Hauing finiſhed theſe thinges, he diſputeth of diuorſe: he reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth and reformeth the olde and holy inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of holy matrimonie:<note n="f" place="margin">In the 10.11 &amp; 12. verſes.</note> he reciteth the kindes of chaſte menne, ſhewing that ſingle life is the ſingular gift of God.<note n="g" place="margin">In the 13.14 and 15. verſes.</note> And becauſe mariage was ordeyned of God cheefly for the procreation of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, he ſheweth next after the reſtitution of mariage, how children are eſteemed of
<pb facs="tcp:19465:24"/> God.<note n="h" place="margin">From the 16 verſe vnto the 21.</note> He bringeth forth alſo the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of a certaine young man, to teach vs therby, that it belongeth to yong men al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to ſeeke the kingdome of God, and that God his deſire is, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> youth be well brought vp. And there is ſhewed, which is the way to heauen:<note n="i" place="margin">From the 21. ver. vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 27.</note> Alſo what the vſe of riches is, and with what minde we muſt poſſeſſe earthly wealth.<note n="k" place="margin">Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the 27. verſe vnto the ende of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chap.</note> Moreouer by occaſion of the Lordes talke, there riſeth nowe an other diſputation about the rewarde of vertues, and how modeſtly they ought to thinke <hi>of them ſelues,</hi> which looke for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes.<note n="*" place="margin">The 20 chap</note> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">From the 1. verſe vnto the 17.</note> And that he might faſten this more deepely in the mindes of all men, he vſeth the ſimilitude of a man that was an houſholder, which hired labourers into his vineyard, whereby hee toucheth the Iewes ſecretly, and doth ſomewhat ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow forth the receiuing of the Gentiles.<note n="m" place="margin">In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 17.18. and 19. verſes.</note> Againe leaſt any, being puffed vp with pride by the name of rewarde, ſhould ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that he is iuſtified by his own works, the Lord preacheth diligently of his own death and reſurrection, that we may vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that we are iuſtified thereby.<note n="n" place="margin">From the 20 verſe vnto the 24</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:19465:24"/> And although he ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> repeted theſe things with great grauitie, yet doth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſh, aſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually to honors, ſeeke not thoſe thinges which are of God, but which are of men. For the mother of <hi>zebedee</hi> his children, her ſonnes not beeing ignorant thereof, aſketh cheefe authoritie of the Lord for her ſonnes.<note n="o" place="margin">In the 24. verſe.</note> Herevpon the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſciples enuie them, and contend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelues ſharply and moſt am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitiouſly.<note n="p" place="margin">From the 25. vnto the 29.</note> But the Lord reduceth al their mindes to humilitie, drawing out that ſame moſt hurtefull poyſon with moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident argumentes.<note n="q" place="margin">From the 29 verſe vnto the ende of the chapter.</note> Laſtly he reſtoreth ſight to the blinde, which craued the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of God, to this ende, that he might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare by all meanes, that he came into the worlde to helpe and ſaue men.<note n="r" place="margin">Wherof Mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thew ſpake be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and wherof he intreateth nowe.</note> 
               <hi>Matthew</hi> deſcribed laſt before, what the Lorde did hitherto in Galilee, and in his iourney from Galilee, as hee went vp to Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, and nowe doth he ſhewe what he did in the holy and royall Citie it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>And the nearer hee draweth to his croſſe and death, the more liuely doeth hee ſhew his wholeſome ſtrength, &amp; moſt holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſetteth forth his worthy power &amp; grace.
<pb facs="tcp:19465:25"/> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">The 21. cha.</note> 
               <note n="s" place="margin">From the 1 verſe vnto the 8.</note> For entering nowe into the holy citie with a very newe and humble pompe, hee ſheweth moſt clearely that he is the verye kinge and deliuerer of Iſrael looked for.<note n="t" place="margin">From the 8. verſe vnto the 12.</note> Hee is receyued with wyllyng mindes and honourably of the common people, that we alſo may learne therby to receiue the Lord truely and religiouſly.<note n="v" place="margin">Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the 12. verſe vnto the 17.</note> And he did in the temple offices very kinglike &amp; prieſtlike, whereat the Phariſees &amp; prieſts almoſt burſt in ſunder for ſpite &amp; hatred.</p>
            <p>For firſte purging the temple from filth, &amp; reforming y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy worſhipping of God, he thruſt the byers and ſellers out of the temple: then takyng care for the poore, he healeth the ſicke.<note n="x" place="margin">In the 17. verſe.</note> And when theſe things were happily accompliſhed he go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth forth of the citie,<note n="y" place="margin">In the 18, &amp; 19. verſes.</note> and curſeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> figge tree, which brought forth no fruite, which forthwith withering, ſhadowed forth by a certaine token, what was imminent to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy citie.<note n="z" place="margin">In the 20, 21 &amp; 22. verſes.</note> Although the Lord by occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion thereof doth teache his diſciples true fayth, and commende vnto them faithfull prayers.<note n="a" place="margin">From the 23 verſe vnto the 28.</note> And returnyng to the temple, as belonged vnto his princely office, hee taught diligently, and ſharpely contended
<pb facs="tcp:19465:25"/> with the enemies of true religion. For whereas they aſked, by what authoritie y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde did thoſe thinges, which he did, hee brydleth them with a contrary queſtion, yea he doeth moſt grauely accuſe them of diſloyalty and impenitent life.<note n="b" place="margin">From the 28 ver. vnto the 33</note> For vnto this purpoſe doeth he bring foorth a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable framed touching two ſonnes, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring his enemies vnto Publicanes and harlottes, that he might ſhewe, that theſe were more religious and more bleſſed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they.<note n="c" place="margin">From the 33 verſe vnto the ende of the cha.</note> Here vnto doth he forthwith ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyne an other ſimilitud of an houſholder, whiche let out his vineyarde to huſbande men or farmers, whereby he doeth liuely paynt foorth the benefites of God and the peuiſh and ſhameleſſe vnthankefulnes of the people of the Iewes, whoſe puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t foorth with hee ſheweth, namely that the Iewes ſhould be caſt off, and that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles ſhoulde bee receiued into their place.<note n="*" place="margin">The 22. chap</note> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the firſt verſe vnto the 15.</note> And vnto the ſame purpoſe alſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyneth the ſimilitude, whiche hee put forth touching them that were bydden to the wedding, ſharpely reprouing the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience and vnbeleefe of the nation of the Iewes, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which they were to be cut
<pb facs="tcp:19465:26"/> off and to be forſaken.<note n="e" place="margin">Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the 15. verſe vnto the 23.</note> Theſe things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing finiſhed, <hi>Matthewe</hi> goeth forewarde, and ſetteth forth plainely certaine graue, ſharpe, and profitable queſtions or diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations handeled betweene the Lord and the lawyers. Firſt of this: whether tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute ought to be paied to <hi>Caeſar?</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">From the 23 verſe vnto the 34.</note> Then, whether the dead riſe againe, and howe they riſe againe?<note n="g" place="margin">From the 34 verſ. vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 41.</note> Moreouer, what the chiefeſt commaundement in the Lawe is: what the ende and matter of the lawe and of the Prophetes is?<note n="h" place="margin">Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the 41. verſe vnto the end of the chap.</note> Afterwardes, how Chriſt, for ſo much as he is the ſonne of Dauid, after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſhe, can be alſo his Lord? All theſe thinges doth our Lord in reſpect of his prieſtly office expounde moſt reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly, moſt learnedly, moſt plainely, and greatly to the profite of the faithfull.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">The 23. chap</note> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">From the 1. ver. of the chap. end of the ſame.</note>Laſtly, when as hee ſawe the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees and the reſt of the rulers of the people to be altogether blinde, indurate, and vncurable, hee inuayeth moſt ſharply againſt them, accuſing them of moſt gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous and vnruly offences: hee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the puniſhment of their miſchiudus deedes, &amp; the moſt terrible deſtruction of the people and of the citie. Al theſe things did our Lord openly, with great authority in the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple, inſtructing his Church here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb facs="tcp:19465:26"/> profitably, diuerſly, &amp; in many pointes.<note n="k" place="margin">A remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of thoſe thinges which haue bin ſpoken of before.</note> Our Lord hath hitherto by the way and yet often ſpoken of the ouerthrowe of the people of the Iewes and of the citie Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem: wherein he comprehended both the caſting off of the Iewes out of the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip of God, and alſo the prophanation of the temple, of the prieſthood, and of all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> woorſhipping, <hi>after the ceremonial law</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">The 24. cha.</note>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the firſt verſe vnto the 42.</note>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And becauſe theſe things ſeemed ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge and incredible, namely that God woulde prophane <hi>and forſake</hi> that people deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from holy parents, and that place, and that worſhipping, &amp; that holy preiſthoode, he doth more fully expounde vnto his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, which inquired <hi>there of,</hi> the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and deſtinie hanging ouer the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and citie, liuely deſcribing, what won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull matters and ſtrange tokens, what troubles, calamities, and miſeries ſhoulde go before that deſtruction: and of what maner, how cruell, horrible, and fearefull that ruine ſhould be. Forthwith by occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the deſtruction of the citie, he reaſoneth alſo of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deſtruction of the world, or of the finiſhing of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, &amp; of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glorious com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the ſonne of man to iudgement:
<pb facs="tcp:19465:27"/> 
               <note n="m" place="margin">Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the 42. verſe vnto the ende of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chap.</note> exhortyng all men to ſober and diligent watchfulnes, propoſing rewardes to the watchfull, and threatning puniſhment to the ſlouthful &amp; ſleepie.<note n="*" place="margin">The 25 chap</note> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the firſt verſe vnto the 31.</note> Which things forthw<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he plainly ſheweth by moſt comely and moſt plentifull ſimilitudes, handeling as well the partes of the watchfull as of the ſleepie.<note n="o" place="margin">Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the 31. verſe vnto the 46.</note> Laſtly <hi>Matthewe</hi> adioyneth a deſcription, or as if it were a certayne fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of the iudge to come, and of his laſte iudgement: wherin y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt ſentence is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced by the ſame iudge againſt al man kinde, ioyful to the good, but moſt ſorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euil. For this matter is thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded:<note n="p" place="margin">In the laſt ver of the chapter.</note> 
               <hi>And theſe ſhall go away into e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting paine: but the righteous into life eternal.</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">A briefe ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of that which foloweth.</note> After all theſe things there is placed, as the finiſhing &amp; the moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect accompliſhing of al our ſaluation, the moſt holy, &amp; moſt profitable hiſtorie of the paſſion &amp; redemption of Chriſt the Lord: wherein he fully executeth all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> offices as wel of a prieſt, as of a king, and in a briefe ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me doth propoſe his greateſt force to be beholden of al men. For he teacheth dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently both by al his wordes and by al his deedes, hee inſtituteth his famous ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, hee prayeth moſt feruently, hee ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificeth
<pb facs="tcp:19465:27"/> for ſinne, hee purgeth ſinners, he deliuereth, he pitieth, hee defendeth his <hi>ſeruants,</hi> and he treadeth downe and puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth the wicked, ſhewing euery where in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible humilitie, and declaring ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time no ſmall glory, when as all the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, being troubled at his death, ſhewed moſt plaine tokens as it were of their great ſorrowe. <hi>Matthew</hi> handeleth all theſe things in a goodly order, &amp; in a pure, plaine, and liuely ſtile.<note n="*" place="margin">The 26. chap.</note> 
               <note n="r" place="margin">In the 1. &amp; 2 verſes.</note> For firſt hee ſheweth the time wherein he ſuffered, and propoſeth the ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me of his paſſion.<note n="ſ" place="margin">From the 3. ver. vnto the 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Then he deſcribeth ſome cauſes of the Lorde his death, proceeding partly from the enuie &amp; malice of the Prieſtes againſt Chriſt, and partly from the couetouſneſſe and horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble treaſon of <hi>Iudas,</hi> which ſold his Lorde to the Senate of Biſhops.<note n="t" place="margin">Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the 17. ver. vnto the 26</note> Hauing fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed the cauſes, he commeth vnto the deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cription of his laſt ſupper: wherein aboue all things he foreſheweth his <hi>Diſciples</hi> both his death, and alſo that hee ſhould bee both betrayed and ſold of his owne: More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer he prouoketh by many meanes the mind of <hi>Iudas</hi> the traitour to repentance: but in vaine.<note n="v" place="margin">From the 26 ver. vnto the 30</note> After this he inſtituteth in it the renowmed Sacrament of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
<pb facs="tcp:19465:28"/> and blood, the remembra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his death, wherein we may ſee the briefe ſumme of our ſaluation &amp; of all godlines.<note n="x" place="margin">In the 30. ver.</note> When as hee had ſupped, hee went out with his diſciples vnto the mount of Oliues,<note n="y" place="margin">In the 31. and 32. verſes.</note> In the way he foreſheweth the great offence, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhold riſe among his diſciples <hi>becauſe of him.</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">In the 33.34 and 35. verſes.</note> But they being bolde enough and raſh enough, and not acknowledging enough their owne infirmitie, do promiſe conſtancie and great faith, <hi>Peter</hi> ſpecially, vnto whome notwithſtanding the Lorde foretelleth his moſt filthie fall.<note n="a" place="margin">In the 36.37 and 38. verſes.</note> In the garden of the mount of Oliues he is mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueilouſly vexed, and pitifully tormented with the feare of death.<note n="b" place="margin">In the 39. verſe.</note> In the meane ſeaſon he prayeth earneſtly and conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, commiteing both himſelfe and all his buſineſſe to God and to his holy will.<note n="c" place="margin">From the 40. verſe vnto the 47.</note> Then doth he diligently waken his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples beeing a ſteepe:<note n="d" place="margin">In the 47. verſe.</note> and whileſt hee was occupied therein, <hi>Iudas</hi> the traitour commeth, bringing with him a rowte of moſt wicked and moſt filthie varlets:<note n="e" place="margin">In the 48. &amp; 49. verſes.</note> foorthwith he kiſſeth his maſter, and with a kiſſe betraieth his Lord to his moſt wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked enemies.<note n="f" place="margin">In the 50. verſe.</note> For the chiefe Prieſtes
<pb facs="tcp:19465:28"/> ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts fal vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord, take him, bind him, &amp; oppreſſe him.<note n="g" place="margin">From the 51. ver. vnto the 55</note> In the mean ſeaſon <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> fighteth vnhappily for his maſter, and is ſtayed by his maſter:<note n="h" place="margin">In the 55. verſe.</note> who alſo foorthwith ſharpely reproueth the open, greeuous, and moſt wicked reproch of the chiefe Prieſtes ſeruants then offered vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him.<note n="i" place="margin">In the 56. ver</note> And whileſt theſe things were thus in doing, all the Diſciples flie from the Lorde.<note n="k" place="margin">In the 57. &amp; 58. verſes.</note> But hee is brought away to <hi>Caiphas</hi> the high Prieſt into the conſiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.<note n="l" place="margin">In the 59.60 and 61. verſes</note> Two thinges were chiefly hande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led there. The Lorde is accuſed before the Prieſtes and the counſell, falſe witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are brought foorth,<note n="m" place="margin">From the 62 ver. vnto the 65</note> the Lorde his cauſe is handeled moſt vniuſtly,<note n="n" place="margin">In the 65. and 66. verſes</note> and at the laſt hee is condemned,<note n="o" place="margin">In the 67. &amp; 68. verſes.</note> buffetted, and moſt vnworthily ſpit vpon.<note n="p" place="margin">From the 66. verſe vnto the end of the chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</note> And withal the filthie and ſhamefull denying of <hi>Peter</hi> is plentifully deſcribed.<note n="*" place="margin">The 27 cap.</note> 
               <note n="q" place="margin">In the 1 and 2. verſes.</note> And when as the ſentence of condemnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced <hi>againſt him,</hi> he is brought forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with from the Prieſtes, and foorth of the Conſiſtorie or hall of the high prieſt, into the iudgemente Hall, vnto <hi>Pontius Pilate</hi> the <hi>Romane</hi> Deputie, vnto whome hee is deliuered as the moſte
<pb facs="tcp:19465:29"/> wicked of all men, and as one hauing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued a moſt vile death.<note n="r" place="margin">In the 3.4. and 5. verſes.</note> The meane while <hi>Iudas</hi> the traitour examining him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe more deepely, and waying his moſte cruell and wicked offence more rightly, goeth into the temple, reſtoreth the traite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous money to the Prieſtes, deſpaireth &amp; moſt horribly hangeth himſelfe.<note n="ſ" place="margin">From the 6. ver. vnto the 11</note> The Prieſts w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the bloodie money buie the pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters field to burie ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers in.<note n="t" place="margin">From the 11. ver. vnto the 27</note> Moreouer <hi>Pontius Pilate</hi> the deputie of the <hi>Romans</hi> inquireth diligently the cauſe, and the chiefe pointes of the accuſation laide a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Lorde by the Prieſtes: and he vnderſtandeth foorthwith, that the enuie of the Prieſtes was the cauſe: therefore hee both pronounceth him innocent, and iudgeth, that hee ought to bee ſet fully at libertie: whereupon hee tryeth ſundrie and many wayes to let him looſe, which had committed none euill. The prieſtes are moſt wickedly earneſt to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, they accuſe, they vrge, they lye, they threaten, yea and they perſwade and prick forward the common people, and at the laſt they ouercome the iudge being wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with their importunate cries, to let
<pb facs="tcp:19465:29"/> them do with the Lord what they liſt, and to deliuer him to his ſouldiers to be cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.<note n="v" place="margin">From the 27 ver. vnto the 35</note> The ſouldierrs therefore moſt cruelly and moſt vnworthily whippe the ſonne of God with ſcourges, they crowne him with a crowne of thornes, they wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him in contempt, they laugh at him, and ſpit vpon him: then they lay his croſſe vpon his ſhoulders, and leade him being halfe dead vnto the place of execution.<note n="x" place="margin">From the 35. ver. vnto the 45</note> There they crucifie him in the middeſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene two moſt wicked theeues, they part his garments as a certaine ſpoile, and ſetting all pitie and curtiſie aſide, they mock him ſuffering moſt bitter torments, as thoogh he had bin deceiued of his hope in God.<note n="y" place="margin">From the 45. ver. vnto the 51.</note> But he, in ſo many &amp; ſo great reproches and torments, continuyng con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly in perfect faith and patience, and ſacrificyng moſt holyly for the ſinnes of all the worlde, cryeth to God the father, vnto whome alſo, at the laſt yeelding vp the Ghoſte, be committeth his moſt holy ſoule.<note n="z" place="margin">From the 51. ver. vnto y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 54.</note> And foorthwith, after hee had giuen vp the Ghoſte, the vaile in the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> is rent <hi>in two peeces,</hi> and certaine ſtrange wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders are wrought
<pb facs="tcp:19465:30"/> both in heauen and earth:<note n="a" place="margin">In the 54, 55 &amp; 56. verſes.</note> wherewith the Centurion an Heathen being moued, doth openly witneſſe, that this Ieſus, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though hee were crucified, was the true ſonne of God.<note n="b" place="margin">From the 57 verſe vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 62</note> After this <hi>Ioſeph</hi> of <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mathea,</hi> a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of very great credit &amp; digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, commeth to <hi>Pilate,</hi> and intreateth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the body of Ieſus might be giuen to him, that he might bury it. <hi>Pilate</hi> graunteth it wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, therefore the body of the Lorde is buried moſt worthilie.<note n="c" place="margin">From the 62 verſe vnto the end of the chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</note> Moreouer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chief of the Iewes fearing that the Lord would riſe againe, requeſt alſo of <hi>Pilate</hi> that a band of ſouldiers might bee giuen them to watch the ſepulchre: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued this bande, they beſet the graue moſt ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gly, &amp; leaſt there might be any deceit wrought, they ſeale the ſtone or couer of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſepulchre, namely that they might reteine &amp; ſtay the liuing <hi>Lord</hi> among the dead.<note n="d" place="margin">The matter conteined in the laſt Chapter.</note> 
               <hi>Mathew</hi> deſcribeth in this laſt chapter the glorious reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Ieſus Chriſte the Lord fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the dead.<note n="*" place="margin">The 28. cha.</note>
               <note n="e" place="margin">In the 1. and 2. verſes.</note> The Angell of the Lord co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth downe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he rolleth backe the ſtone fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the dore of the graue, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth ſhaketh w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> an earthquake, &amp; the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious body of the Lord reſtored to life co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth out forthwith.<note n="f" place="margin">In the 3. &amp; 4. verſes.</note> Moreouer becauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:19465:30"/> angel did ſhine like lightning, the keepers being amaſed, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſtand not the Lord riſing againe, but think <hi>it beſt</hi> to prouide for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues by fleeing away.<note n="g" place="margin">In the 5.6. &amp; 7. verſes.</note> The mean while come the wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſee y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſepulchre, bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſweet odours, which they had prepared. Vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> appeareth the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid angel of the Lord, &amp; teacheth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that Chriſt was riſen in deed, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manding them to depart forthw<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, &amp; to report the reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the diſciples.<note n="h" place="margin">In the 8.9. &amp; 10. verſes.</note> Whileſt they were going their way, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord himſelf met the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhewing himſelf plainly vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reſtored to life, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manding the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to declare his true reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto his diſciples.<note n="i" place="margin">In the 11. verſe.</note> Whileſt theſe things were in doing, thoſe ſouldiers y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> keepers of the ſepulchre, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lately we ſaid left their ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding &amp; fled, came into the citie, &amp; declared to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chiefe Prieſtes thoſe things, which they had ſeen, how y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Angell came down fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen, &amp; rolled backe the ſtone: how Chriſt came forth aliue again, &amp; how bright &amp; fearful y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> forme of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> angel was.<note n="k" place="margin">From the 12 ver. vnto the 16</note> At w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> newes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> prieſts &amp; phariſees being aſtonied &amp; raging, bribed the ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> money, who lying, as they were taught, ſpread abrode among the common people this fooliſhe reporte, that whileſt they ſlept, forſooth the diſciples came and
<pb facs="tcp:19465:31"/> ſtole his body foorth of the Sepulchree.<note n="l" place="margin">In the 16.17 &amp; 18. verſes.</note> But the Lorde Ieſus offering himſelfe to be beholden moſt manifeſtly of his <hi>Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> in <hi>Galilee,</hi> confirmeth them in the truth of faith.<note n="m" place="margin">In the 19. &amp; 20. verſes.</note> And becauſe all thinges which hytherto haue beene declared in this booke concerning the doctrine, the deedes, the death and the reſurrection of Chriſt, doe perteine to the common ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all mankinde, therefore he ſendeth forth his Diſciples as <hi>meſſengers</hi> into al the worlde, commaunding them to baptiſe and to preach the Goſpell to euery crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, promiſing the meane while that hee, although in body he go vp to heauen, will bee with his, and with his holy Churche continually and vnto the ende of the worlde.</p>
            <trailer>Heere endeth the Summe of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell by Saint Matthewe.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="Mark" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:19465:31"/>
            <head>¶<hi>The ſumme of the</hi> Goſpell by Saint Marke</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Aint <hi>Marke</hi> beginneth the hiſtorie of his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell with the baptiſme and doctrine of <hi>Iohn</hi> Baptiſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The</hi> 1. <hi>chap.</hi> In the 1. &amp; 2. verſes.</note> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">From the 3 verſe vnto the 7.</note> ſhewing what he taught,<note n="c" place="margin">In the 7. &amp; 8. verſes.</note> what hee witneſſed of Chriſt the Lorde, howe hee behaued himſelfe,<note n="d" place="margin">In the 9. ver.</note> and how hee baptiſed Chriſt the Lorde.<note n="e" place="margin">In the 10 &amp; 11. verſes.</note> Heere vnto hee ioyneth foorthwith, howe Chriſt was annoynted and reuealed <hi>or made knowen,</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">In the 12 and 13 verſes.</note> howe he was exerciſed and prouoked with greeuous temptation,<note n="g" place="margin">In the 14 &amp; 15 verſes,</note> laſtly how he came abroade, &amp; preached y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdome of God.<note n="h" place="margin">From the 16 verſe vnto the 21.</note> Hee taketh vnto him ſelfe foorthwith from the beginning <hi>of his preaching</hi> witneſſes of his deedes and wordes, calling ſome of them diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, whom he might faſhion and make inſtructors of all the worlde, forſomuch as he came to lighten all the worlde with the doctrine of truth, and to redeeme the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:19465:32"/> from the power of ſinne, of death, of hell, and of Sathan.<note n="i" place="margin">In the 21. &amp; 22. verſes.</note> Herevnto he ioyneth the moſt great effect and vertue of Chriſt his doctrine. For all men are aſtonied at his doctrine.<note n="k" place="margin">From the 23. ver. vnto the 28.</note> Sathan is reſtrayned and caſt out, who geueth place to Chriſte with feare.<note n="l" place="margin">From the 28. ver. vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 40.</note> Afterwardes Chriſte him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and the almightie power of Chriſt is deſcribed by his deedes. For he hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth all diſeaſes,<note n="m" place="margin">From the 40 verſe vnto the end of the chap.</note> hee putteth away all euils,<note n="*" place="margin">The 2. cha.</note>
               <note n="n" place="margin">From the 1. ver. vnto the 13</note> hee forgiueth ſinnes,<note n="o" place="margin">From the 13. ver. vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 18.</note> hee iuſtifieth ſinners and reſtoreth them to their ſoundneſſe.<note n="p" place="margin">In the 1. chap. the 40. ver. and in the 2. chap. the 3, &amp; 4. verſ.</note> The meane while diuers examples are ſette foorth to the faithfull, in them whiche come to Chriſte to craue his helpe, howe wee alſo ought to come vnto Chriſte.<note n="q" place="margin">From the 18 ver. vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 23.</note> Foorthwith the Lorde purgeth the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinges,<note n="r" place="margin">From the 23. verſ. to the end of the chap.</note> and holye dayes of his people from the erroures of the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees,<note n="*" place="margin">The 3. chap.</note> 
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">From the 1. ver. vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 13.</note> and the meane ſeaſon hee ſheweth his ſtrength, proouing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to bee the Sonne of GOD.<note n="t" place="margin">From the 13. ver. vnto the 20</note> Nowe when as by this meanes hee had ſufficiently wonne the heartes of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, that they might nowe beginne to vnderſtande the vertue of Chriſte the
<pb facs="tcp:19465:32"/> Sonne of GOD, hee chooſeth foorth of them twelue, vnto whom he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyneth the charge of preaching the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, and furniſheth them with the power of woorking miracles.<note n="v" place="margin">From the 20 ver. vnto the 31</note> Then hee ſheweth, that the ſucceſſe of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, and the miracles of the Goſpell ought to bee aſcribed to the power of GOD, not to Sathan, or to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gike.<note n="x" place="margin">From the 31 ver. vnto the end of the chap.</note> And hee ſheweth by his owne example, what manner of men the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of God his worde ſhould be, namely ſuch as haue renounced fleſhe and blood, and which are the ſonnes of GOD.<note n="*" place="margin">The 4. chap.</note> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the 1. ver. vnto the end of the chap.</note> By whiche occaſion he reaſoneth forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with plentifully of the ſeede, foorth of which the ſonnes of God growe, that is to ſay, of the hearing or learning of God his woorde, of the effecte, force, ſucceſſe, and fruite of GOD his woorde. All the whiche thinges he propoſeth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrapped and couered with moſte elegant parables. Hee addeth alſo the diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, faultes, and perils, whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God his ſeede is ſubiect, ſetting foorth euerye where in the meane ſeaſon the
<pb facs="tcp:19465:33"/> vertue of Chriſt.<note n="z" place="margin">A reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of that which was ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</note> In the chapters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore goyng many things haue been diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted touching the worde of God.<note n="a" place="margin">The matter co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the 5 6 &amp; 7 chapters.</note> But the onely and moſt certaine purpoſe of the 5, 6, and 7 chapters is Ieſus the Sauiour of the worlde, and faith in him.<note n="*" place="margin">The 5 chap.</note> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">From the firſt verſ. vnto the end of the chap.</note> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that the name of Chriſt the Sauiour might bee more famous, &amp; that the faith in him might be more commended to all Saintes, <hi>Marke</hi> placeth in the 5. chapter three notable hiſtories, whereby he ſetteth foorth euidently the power and vertue of Chriſt, and teacheth faith in Chriſt.<note n="*" place="margin">The 6 chap.</note> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">From the firſt verſe vnto the 4.</note> Then doth he returne againe to the word of God, &amp; to the preaching of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word. For he bringeth in the Lorde preaching in his owne cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trie,<note n="d" place="margin">In the 4, 5, &amp; 6 verſes.</note> who alſo ſharpely accuſed the vnthankfulneſſe of his owne people.<note n="e" place="margin">In the 7 verſe</note> Heereunto he ioyneth in goodly order the ſending foorth of the diſciples to the office of preaching,<note n="f" place="margin">From the 8 verſe vnto the 12.</note> and ſetteth foorth the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, wherwith he inſtructed them being readie to depart.<note n="g" place="margin">In the 12 &amp; 13 verſes.</note> And then doth he alſo touche the obedience and diligence of the diſciples.<note n="h" place="margin">From the 14 verſe vnto the 30.</note> Foorthwith hee ſetteth foorth the worthie hiſtorie of Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt, wherein is propoſed a notable exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb facs="tcp:19465:33"/> of a good and faithfull Preacher, and alſo <hi>declareth</hi> what his end was.<note n="i" place="margin">From the 30 ver. vnto the 45.</note> Againe to the comfort of his miniſters, and for the inſtruction of all the faithfull, the Lorde fedde much people in the wilderneſſe,<note n="k" place="margin">From the 45. verſe vnto the end of the chapt.</note> and deliuered <hi>his diſciples</hi> beyng in peril vpon the ſea.<note n="l" place="margin">What may be learned by the doings of chriſt ſpoken of in this chap. before go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> For ſo doth the Lord wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that he is the foode of the faithfull, that he is the chiefe ſhepheard, that hee gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth ſhepheardes, that he deliuereth thoſe, which call vpon him, from all daungers, and that he bringeth them into a quiet ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. And this much touching the doctrine of the trueth:<note n="*" place="margin">The 7 chap.</note> 
               <note n="m" place="margin">From the 1 verſe vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 14.</note> heereunto <hi>Marke</hi> ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth a treatiſe of mens traditions. The Lorde teacheth to beware of them and to auoyde them.<note n="n" place="margin">From the 14 ver. vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 24.</note> Notwithſtanding leauing forthwith the teachers of mens traditions, he turneth to the people, and expoundeth to them, which is the true pureneſſe of the minde, which is the end of the doctrine of Godlineſſe, euen that the minde of man may bee purged.<note n="o" place="margin">From the 24 verſe vnto the 31.</note> Laſtly by the example of the woman of <hi>Siropheniſſa</hi> true faith in Chriſt is taught,<note n="p" place="margin">From the 31 ver. vnto the end of the chapter.</note> 
               <hi>as alſo by healing the deafe ſtammerer,</hi> is taught how great the goodneſſe and vertue of the Lorde
<pb facs="tcp:19465:34"/> is.<note n="*" place="margin">The 8. chap.</note> 
               <note n="q" place="margin">From the 1. ver. vnto the 11</note> Becauſe faith is the chiefeſt ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of Chriſtians, <hi>Marke</hi> adioyneth cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne thinges, whereby hee teacheth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne and confirmeth the faith of the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the woordes and deedes of the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, healing affection, which greatly diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth faith, and deepely ingraffeth the care of thinges preſent, yea miſtruſt it ſelfe.<note n="r" place="margin">In the 11. &amp; 12. ver.</note> Hereunto he ioyneth an example of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beliefe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Phariſees, ſhewing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief is a moſt heinous offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; wickednes.<note n="ſ" place="margin">From the 12. verſ. vnto 22.</note> He commandeth his <hi>diſciples</hi> to beware of the leauen of the Phariſees.<note n="t" place="margin">Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the 22. ver. vnto the 27</note> After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde hee openeth the eies of a blind man, that it may appeare euen thereby, who o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth the eyes of the minde of the godly.<note n="v" place="margin">From the 27 ver. vnto the 31</note> After this there is added an example of the true confeſſion of the Chriſtian faith.<note n="x" place="margin">In the 31, 32 and 33. ver.</note> Where the Lord diſcuſſeth many thinges touching y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miſteries of faith, how ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is procured for vs by his owne death:<note n="y" place="margin">From the 33 ver. vnto the end of the chapter.</note> &amp; he reaſoneth alſo of the denying of one his ſelfe, or of the mortification of the fleſh.<note n="*" place="margin">The 9. chap.</note> 
               <note n="z" place="margin">From the 1. ver. vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 14</note> Vnto theſe thinges is adioyned the tranſfiguration of the Lorde, that hereby all they, which contemne this preſent life, may haue a taſt of the life to come.<note n="a" place="margin">From the 14. ver. vnto the 30</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:19465:34"/> Afterwarde it is ſhewed by a notable deede, that Ieſus is the <hi>Meſſias</hi> the Sauiour of the worlde, whiche came to deliuer foorth of the power of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Deuill y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faithfull beleeuers, which watch dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with prayers and faſtinges againſt his lying in wayte.<note n="b" place="margin">From the 30 ver<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> vnto the 38</note> And now doth he alſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to his <hi>diſciples,</hi> modeſtie &amp; humility of mind,<note n="c" place="margin">From the 38. ver. vnto the 42</note> admoniſhing the meane while, that wee condemne no man, or vtterlye caſt of any:<note n="d" place="margin">From the 42 verſe vnto the end of the chap.</note> where hee diſputeth alſo of offence, and of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> neceſſitie and vſe of corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.<note n="e" place="margin">The argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the 10. &amp; 11. chap.</note> Now doth Saint <hi>Marke</hi> deſcribe in certayne chapters, certaine choſen and woorthie ſpeaches of the Lorde, vttered touching harde and very neceſſary points for the framing of holy life aright, that therby y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> godly may learne, how to behaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues godly in this world.<note n="*" place="margin">The 10 cha.</note> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">From the 1. ver. vnto the 13</note> And firſt he diſputeth of mariage, which, being defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> phariſees, he pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth, reſtoring it to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> naturall perfection therof.<note n="g" place="margin">From the 13 ver. vnto the 17</note> The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, becauſe childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fruite of mariage, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſecond place he intreateth of them, <hi>ſhewing</hi> what we ſhould thinke of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as touching their ſaluation, teaching y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they muſt be brought to God.<note n="h" place="margin">From the 17. ver. vnto the 23</note> In the thirde place is ſette foorth the famous
<pb facs="tcp:19465:35"/> talke of the Lorde with a verye rich young man: whereby ſundrye thinges are lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: namely that God is the chiefe good: which is the way to heauen: how great y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miſery and folly of man is.<note n="i" place="margin">From the 23 ver. vnto the 28</note> For hee tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth howe hardely riche men enter into the kingdome of God.<note n="k" place="margin">From the 28 ver. vnto the 32</note> After this he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treateth of the rewarde of vertues, and of their modeſtie, which receiue the rewards.<note n="l" place="margin">In the 32, 33 and 34. verſes.</note> Foorthwith hee putteth his diſciples in remembrance of the myſterie of his paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note n="m" place="margin">In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 35, 36, and .37. verſes.</note> In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame place it appeareth manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the requeſt of <hi>Iames</hi> and <hi>Iohn,</hi> how hawtie the fleſhe is. For theſe two re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, that primacie may be graunted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Lorde in the kingdome of Chriſt:<note n="n" place="margin">In the 38, 39 and 40. verſes.</note> whom notwithſtanding he ſo brideleth,<note n="o" place="margin">From the 41. ver vnto the 46</note> that he weedeth out of the reſt alſo ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and enuie, and ſoweth in them mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie and humilitie.<note n="p" place="margin">From the 46. verſe vnto the end of the chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</note> As alſo in the hiſtory of <hi>Bartimeus</hi> he beateth into them faith.<note n="*" place="margin">The 11. cha.</note>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the firſt verſe vnto the 12.</note> After theſe things he entering into the citie of <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> with royall pompe, ſheweth that hee is the true and expected <hi>Meſſias,</hi> the king and prieſt of God his people.<note n="r" place="margin">Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the 15. verſe vnto the 20.</note> Therefore in diſcharge of his office he threwe the byers and ſellers out
<pb facs="tcp:19465:35"/> of the temple.<note n="ſ" place="margin">In the 13. and 14. verſes.</note> Foorthwith hee curſeth the figge tree, wherein he ſhadoweth forth the ſorowfull deſtinies of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">From the 20 verſe vnto the 27.</note> &amp; teacheth faith agayne.<note n="v" place="margin">In the 27. &amp; 28. verſes.</note> The Phariſees and the chiefe of the Iewes oppoſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues againſt him, and aſke him by what authoritie he doth that, which hee doeth?<note n="x" place="margin">Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the 29. verſe vnto the end of the chap.</note> Whom he beateth downe moſt mighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with a contrary queſtion.<note n="*" place="margin">The 12. cha.</note> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">From the 1. verſe vnto the 13.</note> Laſtly he foreſheweth them the iudgement of God, namely their deſtruction and caſting of, which they ſhoulde ſuffer for their owne fault, &amp; not becauſe God is hard to pleaſe.<note n="z" place="margin">From the 13. verſ. vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 35.</note> Moreouer the Lorde anſweareth with marueilous maieſtie vnto certaine queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons very profitable and neceſſarie.<note n="a" place="margin">From the 13. ver. vnto the 18</note> For firſt he reaſoneth of the magiſtrate, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunding to pay vnto him, that whiche we owe him.<note n="b" place="margin">From the 18. ver. vnto the 28</note> Then refuting the <hi>Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces,</hi> beyng the patriarches of the <hi>Vale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinians,</hi> and of the <hi>Marcionites,</hi> he appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the reſurrection of the dead, and the life of the worlde to come.<note n="c" place="margin">From the 28. ver. vnto the 35</note> Afterwards he diſputeth plainely of the ende and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of al the Scripture or of God his lawe.<note n="d" place="margin">From the 35. ver. vnto the 38</note> Moreouer he propoſeth a queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on euen vnto his aduerſaries, whereby he
<pb facs="tcp:19465:36"/> prooueth euidently, that hee is the true <hi>Meſſias,</hi> beeyng of a double nature, namely true GOD and man.<note n="e" place="margin">In the 38, 39 &amp; 40. ver.</note> But becauſe his aduerſaries, I meane the prieſtes and ſcribes, woulde bee mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with no plaineneſſe and manifeſtneſſe of trueth, but went on continually like themſelues, both to ſeduce the common people with their corrupt traditions, and to pill them with their vnſatiable deſire of hauing, the Lorde admoniſheth the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people, and commaundeth them to beware of their doctrine. Beſides all this he layeth manie and greate offences to their charges, and among the reſt couetouſneſſe and ſacrileges.<note n="f" place="margin">From the 41 ver. vnto the end of the chapter.</note> And yet leaſt any ſhoulde thinke, that riches are beſtowed in vayne for the mayntenance of the affaires of the Churche, hee doth much commende the gifte of a certayne widowe caſt into the treaſurie.<note n="*" place="margin">The 13. cha.</note> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">In the 1, &amp; 2. verſes.</note> Laſt of all, hee foreſheweth and payn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth foorth the deſtruction and ruine of the moſt gorgious temple of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> of the moſt auncient citie, and of all the worlde.<note n="h" place="margin">From the 3. ver. vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 33.</note> Hee addeth alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſignes and calamities, which ſhoulde goe before,
<pb facs="tcp:19465:36"/> to foreſhewe ſuch euils as can not bee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed.<note n="i" place="margin">From the 33 ver. vnto the end of the chapter.</note> And becauſe the Lord deſireth to ſaue mankinde and not to deſtroy <hi>vs,</hi> hee exhorteth all men to prayers and watchfulneſſe.<note n="k" place="margin">Whereof <hi>Marke</hi> ſpeaketh in the 14. and 15. chap.</note> Nowe <hi>Marke</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to the abſolute perfection of our ſaluation, namely to the deſcription of the wholeſome ſacrifice, and of our redemption through Chriſt his death.<note n="*" place="margin">The 14. cha.</note> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">From the 1. verſe vnto the 12.</note> Wherein firſt hee reciteth the cauſes of his death, ſo farre foorth as apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyneth to the aduerſaries of Chriſte, I meane the prieſtes and <hi>Iudas</hi> the tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour, whiche beeyng blinded with co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe and enuie ſolde the Lorde for a moſte vile price.<note n="m" place="margin">From the 12 ver. vnto the 26</note> Then hee ſpeaketh of that laſt ſupper, wherein the Lorde ſharpely accuſeth the wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of <hi>Iudas</hi> ſpeaking of it at large, and inſtituteth the ſacrament and memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall of our redemption.<note n="n" place="margin">In the 26. ver</note> After that hee goeth foorth into the mount of <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liues,</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">From the 27 ver. vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 32.</note> hee reaſoneth in the waye of that greeuous offence, wherein the diſciples ſhoulde fall, chiefly <hi>Peter.</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">From the 32 ver. vnto the 43</note> Hee prayeth to his Father humblye in the mount, and awaketh his
<pb facs="tcp:19465:37"/> diſciples ſleeping.<note n="q" place="margin">From the 43. ver. vnto the 47</note> The meane while <hi>Iudas</hi> commeth haſtely with a bande of murderers, and betrayeth the Lorde with a kiſſe, who foorthwith is taken by the wicked myniſters.<note n="r" place="margin">In the 47 ver</note> In that hurlye burly <hi>Peter</hi> draweth his ſworde, and figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in vayne.<note n="ſ" place="margin">From the 48. ver. vnto the 53</note> But the Lorde rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth grauelye the vniuſt force of his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimies.<note n="t" place="margin">In the 53. &amp; 54. verſes.</note> Notwithſtanding Chriſte is brought bounden to the high prieſt. The chiefe Biſhoppe calleth foorthwith a counſell of elders and prieſtes againſt the Lorde.<note n="v" place="margin">From the 55 ver. vnto the 60</note> Therein falſe witneſſes are ſought foorth to deſtroy Chriſt, but in vayne.<note n="x" place="margin">From the 60. ver. vnto the 66</note> The high Prieſt riſing vp, deſireth to picke a cauſe of death by a queſtion from Chriſt, and aſketh, whether he be the ſonne of God the true <hi>Meſſias?</hi> And when as the Lord had graunted it and confirmed it, iudgement of death was giuen out againſt him by all the councell.<note n="y" place="margin">From the 66 ver. vnto the end of the chapter.</note> The meane while <hi>Peter</hi> denieth the Lorde in the high prieſt his pallace.<note n="*" place="margin">The 15. cha.</note> 
               <note n="z" place="margin">In the 1. ver.</note> And when the dawnyng was come, Ieſus is leadde to <hi>Pilate</hi> the deputie.<note n="a" place="margin">From the 2. ver. vnto the 12</note> But he trieth and practiſeth many wayes, if hee might deliuer him,
<pb facs="tcp:19465:37"/> whom hee knewe to bee innocent.<note n="b" place="margin">From the 12 ver. vnto the 22</note> But beyng ouercome with the wicked cries of the people, he deliuered Ieſus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſcourged to the ſouldiers to bee cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified.<note n="c" place="margin">From the 22. ver. vnto the 27</note> Hee is therefore lead awaye into the place of Caluarie, <hi>that is to ſaye of a ſkull,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">In the 27. &amp; 28. verſes.</note> where hee is crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the middeſt betweene two theeues,<note n="e" place="margin">From the 29. ver. vnto the 33</note> and hauing ſuffered both diuers tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes and tauntes,<note n="f" place="margin">From the 33. ver. vnto the 38</note> at the laſt hee gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vppe the Ghoſte.<note n="g" place="margin">From the 38. ver. vnto the 42</note> Foorthwith ſtraunge ſignes are ſhewed, wherewith the Centurion beyng moued, pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth Chriſt to be the ſonne of GOD.<note n="h" place="margin">Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the 42. verſe vnto the end of the chap.</note> And in the euening of the ſame day he is buried moſt decently by <hi>Ioſeph</hi> an honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and a godlye man.<note n="*" place="margin">The 16. cha.</note> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the 1. ver. vnto the 9.</note> But the thirde day hee riſeth againe from the dead, hauing vanquiſhed death, the which thing is expounded moſte euidently by the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell to the women comming to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre.<note n="k" place="margin">Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the 9. ver vnto the 15.</note> Afterwards <hi>Marke,</hi> beeyng about to finiſhe briefely his hiſtorie begun of Chriſt, collecteth and knitteth together certayne ſure argumentes, or euident te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies, whereby hee may proue that the Lorde is riſen in deede from the dead.
<pb facs="tcp:19465:38"/> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">From the 15 ver. vnto the 19</note> Laſt of all, hee ſetteth foorth the 3. chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt poyntes of our religion, that is to ſay the laſt deede of the Lorde, wherein hee ordayned the Eccleſiaſticall order.<note n="m" place="margin">In the 19. verſe.</note> Then hee ſheweth the Aſcenſion of the Lorde into heauen.<note n="n" place="margin">In the 20. ver</note> After this hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth the moſt exacte faithfulneſſe of the Apoſtles of the Lorde, and the happie ſucceſſe thereof. For they did all things ſo as the Lorde had commaunded, and the Lorde wrought with them, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> foorth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the moſt holy Church roſe vp in the worlde.</p>
            <trailer>Heere endeth the Summe of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell by Saint Marke.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="Luke" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:19465:38"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               <hi>The ſumme of the</hi> Goſpell by Saint Luke.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the preface placed before this Euangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call worke,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The</hi> 1. <hi>chap.</hi> From the 1. ver. vnto the 5</note> 
               <hi>Luke</hi> ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the cauſes, whiche mooued him to write, and alſo propoſeth the ſumme of his whole purpoſe.<note n="b" place="margin">In the 5, 6, and 7. verſes.</note> Then hee beginneth to penne the hiſtorie, beginning it with the birth of the forerunner of the <hi>Meſſias.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee deſcribeth diligently the parentes of <hi>Iohn</hi> Baptiſt,<note n="c" place="margin">From the 8. ver. vnto the 18</note> chiefly howe both the conception and the office of the ſonne were ſhewed to his father by <hi>Gabriel.</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the 18. ver. vnto the 23</note> whiche thinges when as his father belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued not, it came to paſſe, that hee was made dumbe, for the puniſhment of his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleefe,<note n="e" place="margin">In the 23, 24 &amp; 25. verſes.</note> &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his mother notwithſtanding, God performing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which he had promiſed, did conceaue.<note n="f" place="margin">In the 26. verie.</note> Now after the deſcription of the conceptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> forerunner, he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth downe to deſcribe the incarnation of the
<pb facs="tcp:19465:39"/> very <hi>Meſſias</hi> alſo. Therefore after the noting of the time,<note n="g" place="margin">In the 27. ver</note> hee ſheweth the kinred and condition of his mother, <hi>namelie</hi> that ſhee was a pure virgin of the ſtocke of <hi>Dauid:</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">In the 26. ver</note> vnto whom the very ſame <hi>Gabriel</hi> beyng the meſſenger of the eternall GOD came downe from heauen,<note n="i" place="margin">From the 28. ver. vnto the 32</note> and ſhewed her that it ſo plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the eternall Godhead, that ſhee ſhoulde bee made y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mother of the <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias:</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">In the 32. and 33. verſes.</note> and hee declareth heerewith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, who, and howe greate this childe ſhoulde be.<note n="l" place="margin">In the 34. ver</note> And whereas the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine did not yet fully vnderſtand ſo harde a matter,<note n="m" place="margin">In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 35. ver.</note> the whole reaſon and maner of the incarnation is expounded vnto her by the Angell, that ſhee ſhoulde conceiue by the holy Ghoſt, and bring foorth the very ſonne of GOD.<note n="n" place="margin">In the 36 and 37. verſes.</note> And ſhee is confirmed by the example of <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">In the 38. verſe.</note> The which woordes when as ſhee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeueth, ſhee conceiueth.<note n="p" place="margin">From the 39 ver. vnto the 46</note> And foorth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſhee goeth with all ſpeede to <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth,</hi> &amp; they two haue diuine talke the one with the other.<note n="q" place="margin">From the 46. ver. vnto the 57</note> In this communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the incarnation of the ſonne of God is reuealed, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth of God, his mercie
<pb facs="tcp:19465:39"/> and his power are prayſed, chiefly in the virgin Maries ſong of prayſe and thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing.<note n="r" place="margin">From the 57. ver. vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 59.</note> Moreouer Elizabeth bringeth forth a ſonne,<note n="ſ" place="margin">From the 59. ver. vnto the 64</note> who is named <hi>Iohn.</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">From the 64. ver. vnto the 67</note> Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his father, hytherto dumbe for his vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe, is nowe reſtored the vſe of his tongue, which hee vſeth foorthwith in ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting foorth the prayſes of God.<note n="v" place="margin">From the 67. ver. vnto the 76</note> For hee alſo ſingeth a ſong of praiſes, wherein he prayſeth the truth of God in his promiſes, his goodnes &amp; iuſtice in his deedes.<note n="x" place="margin">In the 76. &amp; 77. verſes.</note> The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he propheſieth certaine thinges of the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of his ſonne,<note n="y" place="margin">From the 78. ver. vnto the end of the chapter.</note> and of the benefites to be beſtowed vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world through Chriſt.<note n="*" place="margin">The 2. chap.</note> 
               <note n="z" place="margin">The argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the chapter.</note> Which things being finiſhed, <hi>Luke</hi> breaketh of the hiſtorie concerning <hi>Iohn,</hi> &amp; maketh haſt to deſcribe the natiuitie of Chriſt.<note n="a" place="margin">In the 1.2. &amp; 3. verſes.</note> Therefore he ſheweth the time,<note n="b" place="margin">In the 4. &amp; 5. verſes.</note> and deſcribeth the place of the natiuitie of the Lord,<note n="c" place="margin">In the 6. &amp; 7 verſes</note> and the maner therof.<note n="d" place="margin">From the 8. ver. vnto 13.</note> And the angell appeareth againe, &amp; publiſheth the birth of the <hi>Mesſias</hi> to the ſhepherds, and expoundeth vnto them the fruite of his natiuitie.<note n="e" place="margin">In the 13. &amp; 14. verſes.</note> In the which place all the heauenly hoſt flocketh together with mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueylous thankefull reioycing, ſinging a birth ſongue to their newe borne King.
<pb facs="tcp:19465:40"/> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">In the 15. verſe.</note> And the ſhepheardes ſeeke the childe, which was borne, with great diligence, as they were commaunded,<note n="g" place="margin">In the 16. ver</note> they finde him,<note n="h" place="margin">Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the 17. verſe vnto the 21.</note> they wonder, and publiſh to all men the greate workes of God.<note n="i" place="margin">In the 21. ver</note> Nowe the childe is circumciſed the eight day, and is named <hi>IESVS.</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">In the 22.23 and 24. verſes.</note> Then he is preſented alſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord in the temple of <hi>Hieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the maner of the firſt begotten ſonnes.<note n="l" place="margin">From the 25. ver. vnto the 34</note> Whereby God his ordinance <hi>Simeon</hi> the iuſt commeth in, which receiueth the little childe into his armes, reioyſeth, &amp; in reioyſing ſheweth howe great things the Father hath giuen vs in his ſonne:<note n="m" place="margin">In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 34, &amp; 35 verſes.</note> &amp; therewithal he propheſieth of his croſſe, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> many ſhould ſtumble at him through vnbeliefe.<note n="n" place="margin">From the 36 ver. vnto the 40</note> And there is alſo <hi>Anne</hi> a wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe of moſt commendable life, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo herſelfe giueth thankes to God, and prayſeth the great benefite of the father in the ſonne <hi>giuen vnto vs.</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">From the 40. ver. vnto the 51</note> Afterwards <hi>Luke</hi> toucheth in fewe wordes the child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, grouth, and youth of Chriſte the Lorde. For he declareth howe hee bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing twelue yeres of age, beeing ſought by his parentes ſorowfully, was founde in the Temple among the Doctors, diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb facs="tcp:19465:40"/> ſo of the chiefeſt pointes of religion, that all wondered at it.<note n="p" place="margin">In the 51, &amp; 52 verſes.</note> Whereunto hee addeth, that, leauing the diſputation, he was obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto his parents: leauing it as it were to be eſteemed by theſe moſt aſſured tokens, of what ſort al his growe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and young age was. And thus hath <hi>Luke</hi> comprehended in a merueilous brief ſumme whatſoeuer ſeemeth to be profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and neceſſarie to bee knowen and to be beleeued touching the Parentage of Chriſt, his childhood, his grouth, &amp; youth.<note n="q" place="margin">What went before.</note> In the two chapters before going there is an entrance made into the matter han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deled in this Goſpell:<note n="r" place="margin">What follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</note> But nowe <hi>Luke</hi> ſetteth foorth the beginning of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, the wonderfull progreſſe and ſucceſſe thereof,<note n="*" place="margin">The 3. cha.</note> 
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">In the firſt &amp; 2 verſes.</note> 
               <hi>ſhewing</hi> at what time,<note n="t" place="margin">In the 2. &amp; 3 verſes.</note> in what place,<note n="v" place="margin">In the 2. and 3 verſes.</note> by whome, and howe, both Chriſt himſelfe and his Goſpel was prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched openly, namely by <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">In the 3 verſe alſo.</note> which baptized and taught in a great aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of men.<note n="y" place="margin">From the 4. verſe vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 10.</note> And hee giueth foorth certaine taſtes of the preaching of <hi>S. Iohn</hi> what he taught al men generally,<note n="z" place="margin">Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the 10. verſe vnto the 15.</note> what certain me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> particularly,<note n="a" place="margin">From the 15. ver. vnto the 19</note> to be brief what he taught, &amp; what things he witneſſed of
<pb facs="tcp:19465:41"/> 
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:19465:41"/> 
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:19465:42"/> 
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:19465:42"/> 
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:19465:43"/> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">In the 19 &amp; 20 verſes</note> Laſtly, he noteth, that for the preaching of the truth, he was caſt into priſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by king <hi>Herod.</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Wherof he ſpeaketh next.</note> Which thinges being in deede briefly knit together, (&amp; yet in ſuch ſort as might be ſufficient for the godly Reader) hee paſſeth ouer to the deſcription of the affayres of the Sauiour himſelfe our Lorde Ieſus Chriſte, whoſe forerunner <hi>Iohn</hi> was:<note n="d" place="margin">In the 21. and 22. verſes.</note> and foorthwith in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning hee teacheth, who hee was, and howe great thinges wee haue from him, he was anointed and authoriſed, by the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the King and Prieſt of the people of god, namely in that he was anoynted with the holy Ghoſte, that hee is the ſonne of of God and of man,<note n="e" place="margin">From the 23. ver. vnto the end of the chapter.</note> for the which cauſe hee draweth foorth along his genealogie or pedegrue euen vnto <hi>Adam.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">The 4. cha.</note> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">From the firſt ver. vnto the 14</note> More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer our Lorde being authoriſed in his function, and kingdome, and Prieſthood, according to his office beginneth nowe to work our ſaluation, and firſt ſetting vpon Satan, hee ouercommeth him in an harde conflict, &amp; at the laſt putteth him to flight.<note n="g" place="margin">In the 14. &amp; 15. verſes.</note> And being a conquerour hee commeth foorth and publiſheth the Goſpell of the kingdome and of deliuerance throughout
<pb facs="tcp:19465:43"/> all <hi>Galilee.</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">From the 16 ver. vnto the 22.</note> Hee hath left deſcribed an excellent taſt of his preaching, namely his ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> city <hi>Nazareth.</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the 22. ver, vnto the 31</note> But whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as his wholeſome doctrine was not ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued of the Citizens of <hi>Nazareth,</hi> as had becomed them, leauing them,<note n="k" place="margin">In the 31. &amp; 32 verſes.</note> hee went to the famous citie <hi>Capernaum,</hi> where hee teacheth againe.<note n="l" place="margin">The vſe of my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles.</note> And he ioyneth cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine wonderfull deedes to his doctrine, whereby he approued y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which hee taught, namely y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is the Sauiour of the world.<note n="m" place="margin">From the 33 ver. vnto the 38</note> Therefore hee deliuereth a man poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with a Diuell by caſting out the deuil:<note n="n" place="margin">In the 38. &amp; 39. verſes.</note> hee reſtoreth to health <hi>Peter</hi> his wiues mother, which was ſick of a feuer:<note n="o" place="margin">In the 40. &amp; 41, verſes.</note> and to be briefe he cureth all kinde of diſeaſes:<note n="p" place="margin">In the 42.43. &amp; 44. ver.</note> But the meane while he preacheth the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel diligently:<note n="*" place="margin">The 5. cha.</note>
               <note n="q" place="margin">From the firſt ver. vnto the 12</note> the which becauſe his will is, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it ſhould be preached co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually in the Church, he chooſeth to himſelf cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine witneſſes, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he draweth vnto him by working of a myracle.<note n="r" place="margin">From the 12 ver. vnto the 17</note> Hee declareth againe by his workes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is the Sauiour of the worlde. For he cleanſeth a Leper:<note n="ſ" place="margin">From the 17. verſe vnto the 27.</note> He healeth a man ſick of a palſie, in whom alſo he declareth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he forgiueth ſinnes to me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note n="t" place="margin">From the 27 verſ. vnto the 33</note> And therfore he calleth &amp; iuſtifieth a
<pb facs="tcp:19465:44"/> notable Publicane, <hi>Leui,</hi> and defendeth him iuſtified, and himſelfe alſo from the malicious detractions of his enemies.<note n="v" place="margin">In the 33.34 &amp; 35. verſes.</note> Where hee ioyneth aptly certaine diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of faſting and prayers,<note n="x" place="margin">Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the 36. verſe vnto the end of the chap.</note> of fit and vnfit hearers of the Goſpell,<note n="*" place="margin">The 6 chap.</note> 
               <note n="z" place="margin">From the firſt ver. vnto the 12.</note> of the Sabboth and of holy dayes, whereby hee reproueth errours and abuſes, and reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the true doctrine, maintaineth the ſame.<note n="y" place="margin">Why the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles were called.</note> Hytherto our Lorde &amp; Redeemer Chriſte was made knowen vnto his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, called for this purpoſe peculiarlie, that they might be inſtructed and made the maſters <hi>and teachers</hi> of all the nations in the earth,<note n="z" place="margin">From the 12 ver. vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 17.</note> vnto them hee adioyneth now certaine other alſo, all the which he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrating commaundeth to bee Apoſtles, that is to ſay Legates or Ambaſſadours, whome at the laſt hee might ſende into the worlde.<note n="a" place="margin">In the 17.18 &amp; 19. verſes.</note> But before he ſendeth them foorth, he inſtructeth them more fully and more familiarly. For hee declareth againe to them, who he is, what he is able to doe, marking foorth moreouer what kinde of doctrine they ſhoulde followe. For in his deedes hee ſheweth diuine vertue:<note n="b" place="margin">From the 20 verſe vnto the 24.</note> and in his woordes hee teacheth which is the
<pb facs="tcp:19465:44"/> true doctrine, which is the true felicitie,<note n="c" place="margin">In the 24.25 &amp; 26. verſes.</note> which is infelicitie,<note n="d" place="margin">From the 27. verſe vnto the 39.</note> which are the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of godlineſſe of the faithfull, and that the Lorde doth exact moſt perfect iuſtice of his <hi>ſeruantes.</hi> For <hi>Luke</hi> ſetteth downe the whole Sermon of the Lorde made in the great aſſembly of men, and in the middeſt of his Diſciples.<note n="e" place="margin">From the 39. verſ. vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 46.</note> In the which Sermon among other things, the Lorde warneth vs diligently, that we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of falſe teachers, of whom hee reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not vndiligently,<note n="f" place="margin">From the 46. verſ. vnto the end of the chap.</note> adding in the end of the Sermon, that it is not enough to heare the worde of God, except wee doe expreſſe in godly deedes, that which wee haue learned in the woorde.<note n="*" place="margin">The 7. chap.</note> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">The vſe of myracles.</note> Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this Sermon of the Lorde <hi>Luke</hi> ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth againe deedes, whereby the Lorde ſheweth his ſauing vertue.<note n="h" place="margin">From the 1. ver. vnto the 11</note> For hee reſtoreth the Centurion his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant.<note n="i" place="margin">From the 11. ver. vnto the 18</note> Then hee rayſeth vp from the dead the ſonne of a certaine widowe of <hi>Nain,</hi> ſhewing thereby that hee is the Lord of life &amp; death.<note n="k" place="margin">In the 18.19 and 20. verſes.</note> And the Diſciples of <hi>Iohn</hi> are there, &amp; propoſe a queſtion to the Lorde:<note n="l" place="margin">In the 21.22 &amp; 23. verſes.</note> by occaſion whereof hee
<pb facs="tcp:19465:45"/> declareth him ſelfe to bee that looked fo <hi>Mesſias.</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">From the 24 ver. vnto the 29</note> And then he extolleth <hi>Iohn</hi> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> moſt ample prayſes, that hee might moue the more to beleeue his witnes, which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly witneſſed that Ieſus was Chriſte.<note n="n" place="margin">From the 29 verſe vnto the 36.</note> Laſtly hee moſt ſharply reprooueth the want of beliefe of the Phariſees, whereby he ſheweth, that it came to paſſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed through their owne vice and fault.<note n="o" place="margin">From the 36 verſe vnto the ende of the chapter.</note> Forthwith he addeth an example, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it may euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly appeare, how y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees truſting too much in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues refuſe Chriſt, &amp; howe ſinners beleeuing receiue him, &amp; there is brought in a ſinfull woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her ſinnes be freely forgiue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the Phariſees ſpeaking much againſt it.<note n="*" place="margin">The 8. chap.</note> 
               <note n="p" place="margin">Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the 1. ver. vnto the 22.</note> Theſe thinges being in this maner ſette foorth, <hi>Luke</hi> bringeth in againe the Lorde teaching, and the people flocking to him in very great companies, whereby they giue him occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to teach by a ſimilitude, what y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nature of the word of God is, what diuerſitie there is of hearers, and that hee doth not approue all hearers, but the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> only which bring forth fruite.<note n="q" place="margin">From the 22 verſe vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 26</note> After theſe thinges is placed the deſcription of a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt, and howe a calme was reſtored
<pb facs="tcp:19465:45"/> by the Lorde to the diſciples, which were merueilouſly troubled, who here alſo, as well as other where often, doeth declare, that he hath power ouer tempeſts,<note n="r" place="margin">From the 26. ver. vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 41.</note> and that he is the conquerour of Satan. For with no weapons, but with his word only he caſteth out and putteth to flight all the legion of Deuils.<note n="ſ" place="margin">From the 41. ver. vnto the 49</note> Moreouer hee hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth a certaine woman beeing troubled with an iſſue of blood, whiche coulde not bee cured,<note n="t" place="margin">From the 49. ver. vnto the end of the chapter.</note> and rayſeth from the dead <hi>Iairus</hi> his daughter. In all theſe things hee inſtructeth in true faith and godlines the mindes of the faithfull, and chiefly of his diſciples,<note n="*" place="margin">The 9. chap.</note> 
               <note n="v" place="margin">In the 1. &amp; 2 verſes.</note> whom, being nowe a good while inſtructed, hee ſendeth forth at the laſt to the office of preaching,<note n="x" place="margin">From the 3. ver. vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 10.</note> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing them certaine peculier preceptes, whiche preſcribed vnto them howe they ſhoulde behaue them ſelues.<note n="y" place="margin">In the 10. ver</note> And the Lorde very frendly receiueth them retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and hauing diſpatched their buſineſſe happely,<note n="z" place="margin">In the 11. ver</note> inſtructing them nowe more fully, that he might prepare the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter matters, and confirme them in the trueth.<note n="a" place="margin">From the 12 ver. vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 18.</note> Hee maketh the people a feaſt.<note n="b" place="margin">In the 18. and 19. verſes.</note> He aſketh, whome the people ſay that
<pb facs="tcp:19465:46"/> he is,<note n="c" place="margin">In the 20. verſe.</note> and what the diſciples thinke of him:<note n="d" place="margin">In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 20 ver. alſo, and in the 21, and 22. verſes.</note> where the confeſſion of a true faith is ſet foorth.<note n="e" place="margin">From the 23 ver. vnto the 28</note> In the ſame place he teacheth the denying of ones ſelfe:<note n="f" place="margin">From the 28 ver. vnto the 37</note> and is tranſformed in the ſight of the cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen diſciples.<note n="g" place="margin">From the 37 ver. vnto the 44</note> And he ouercometh and putteth to flight againe the Deuill rebelling and moſt fiercely raging.<note n="h" place="margin">In the 44 &amp; 45. verſes.</note> Hee intreateth of his paſſion and death:<note n="i" place="margin">In the 46 47. &amp; 48 ver.</note> And forthwith hee teacheth moſt diligently his diſciples humilitie &amp; modeſtie, &amp; he pluck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vp by the roote ambition and pride.<note n="k" place="margin">In the 49. and 50 verſes.</note> where he teacheth alſo that no man is to be contemned or reiected, whiche by any maner of meanes ſeteth forward the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of Chriſt. And in this wiſe did he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whom he purpoſed to make the teachers of the worlde, &amp; in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the whole church.<note n="l" place="margin">What follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</note> Hitherto bleſſed <hi>Luke</hi> hath decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red copiouſly &amp; plainely enough, what the Lorde ſaide and did in Galilee, but hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth he will ſhew the Lord his iourney to the fatal citie of Hieruſalem, what fell out in the way, what he taught, and what won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull and famous thinges he did.<note n="m" place="margin">In the 51.52, &amp; 53. ver.</note> And in the beginning of the iourney the <hi>Samaritanes</hi> denie the Lorde lodging,
<pb facs="tcp:19465:46"/> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">In the 54.55, &amp; 56. ver.</note> but the diſciples, which deſired that their vncourteſie might bee puniſhed, are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooued of the Lorde as inflamed with prepoſterous zeale.<note n="o" place="margin">In the 57 &amp; 58 verſes.</note> Then the Lord repelleth a certaine other man offering the Lorde friendſhip:<note n="p" place="margin">Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the 59. verſe vnto the end of the chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</note> Forthwith cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling two other, hee teacheth howe he will be receiued, and howe he muſt bee folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.<note n="*" place="margin">The 10. chapter.</note> 
               <note n="q" place="margin">In the 1. verſe.</note> Moreouer that the wholeſome doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of the Goſpell might bee made kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen to the more, he chooſeth to him ſelfe more diſciples. For vnto thoſe twelue he adioyneth moreouer other ſeuenty. Theſe he ſent before two &amp; two into euery place whether he himſelfe would come.<note n="r" place="margin">From the 2 ver. vnto the 17</note> Into them he giueth certaine preceptes, and by that meanes hee beginneth againe to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate of teachers, and of the doctrine of the Goſpel.<note n="s" place="margin">In the 17 ver</note> The diſciples faithfully do y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements, &amp; returning declare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lorde, howe happely their buſineſſe fell out. Here he ſheweth, that the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the deuill is deſtroyed by prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the Goſpell:<note n="t" place="margin">In the 18, 19 and 20 ver.</note> hee teacheth his <hi>diſciples</hi> humilitie leaſt they ſhoulde bee puffed vp with pride through the happie handelyng of their affayres:
<pb facs="tcp:19465:47"/> 
               <note n="v" place="margin">In the 21. ver</note> and forthwith hee ſheweth who are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of the worde of the Goſpel,<note n="x" place="margin">In the 22. ver</note> and why all thinges are giuen vnto Chriſt on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the preaching of the Goſpell,<note n="y" place="margin">In the 23. &amp; 24. verſes.</note> alſo howe great their happineſſe is, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue the Goſpell of Chriſte.<note n="z" place="margin">In the 25. ver.</note> And bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aptly aſked by a certaine lawyer, what he ſhoulde do, that he might obtayne euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life,<note n="a" place="margin">In the 26. verſe.</note> he teacheth plainely, which is the ſyncere doctrine,<note n="b" place="margin">In the 27 verſe.</note> 
               <hi>which</hi> is the onely and certayne ende of the ſcripture,<note n="c" place="margin">In the 28. verſe.</note> which is the true preaching of the truth, whiche the teacher of the Goſpell ſhoulde deliuer to the Church,<note n="d" place="margin">From the 29. ver. vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 38.</note> where hee doth chiefly teach vs the loue of our neighbour by bringing in a parable of a man ſlayne by theeues,<note n="e" place="margin">In the 38.40. &amp; 41. ver.</note> and by commending the dueties of <hi>Martha,</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">In the 39, &amp; 42. verſes.</note> before whome the meane ſeaſon hee preferreth the faith of <hi>Marie.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">The 11. cha.</note> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">From the 1. ver. vnto the 14</note> And becauſe prayer in the Churche is nexte to the preaching of the worde, and as it were adioyned therevnto, therefore doth he alſo intreat therof large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and diligently.<note n="h" place="margin">From the 14 verſe vnto the 27.</note> Forthwith by caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth and conquering the Diuell, hee declareth, which of the pointes of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell is chiefe, that he came into the worlde
<pb facs="tcp:19465:47"/> to ouercome the Diuell, and to deſtroye his workes: and that he doth and ſayeth al thinges, not furniſhed with arte <hi>Magike,</hi> or forced by the power of Satan, but tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe the power of God, ſeeing he is the ſonne of God and the true <hi>Meſſias.</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">In the 27 &amp; 28 verſes.</note> He returneth againe to the commendation of the preaching of the Goſpell,<note n="k" place="margin">From th 29. ver. vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 33</note> where he doeth moſt grauely accuſe the neglecting and contemning of the worde of God, and the vnbeliefe of the Iewes.<note n="l" place="margin">From the 33 ver. vnto the 37</note> Moreouer he ſheweth, what the word of God is, why it is reueled to men, howe great the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe, profitablens, and neceſſitie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is.<note n="m" place="margin">From the 37 verſe vnto the end of the chap.</note> Ouer againſt the which is direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly placed falſe doctrine, and the Phariſees and falſe teachers are moſt ſharply chidde of the Lorde,<note n="*" place="margin">The 12. chapter.</note> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">In in the 1.2, &amp; 3, verſes.</note> whoſe doctrine at the laſt he moſt diligently commandeth to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of.<note n="o" place="margin">From the 4. ver vnto the 13</note> And becauſe that can not bee done without the hatred of the worlde, hee exhorteth his <hi>diſciples</hi> alſo to boldneſſe &amp; conſtantnes, not to be in feare for them ſelues, but to behaue them ſelues ſtoutly, and to confeſſe the trueth freely.<note n="p" place="margin">From the 13 ver. vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 35.</note> The deſire of gaine, and chiefly couetouſneſſe, doth hinder and trouble ſyncere religion,
<pb facs="tcp:19465:48"/> the Lord therefore bringing many things againſt couetouſnes, teacheth euery man to be content with his owne eſtate:<note n="q" place="margin">From the 35 ver. vnto the 41</note> he ſetteth foorth againe watchfulneſſe and ſoberneſſe of minde, <hi>neceſſarie</hi> for all tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but for the apoſtles chiefly,<note n="r" place="margin">From the 41 ver. vnto the 49</note> vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by propoſing a ſimilitude, hee ſhadoweth forth againe their duetie,<note n="s" place="margin">From the 49 verſe vnto the 54.</note> adding againe what the effect of the woorde of God is,<note n="t" place="margin">From the 54 ver. vnto the end of the chapter.</note> and admoniſhing vs, that we doe not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne the ſignes of our ſaluation, but that wee receiue it with moſt redie minds.<note n="v" place="margin">What went before.</note> In the chapters before going the Lord intreated of many thinges, by the report of <hi>Luke</hi> the hiſtorian, touching the Goſpel and the preachers of the Goſpel. Nowe the Goſpell ſtandeth of Repentaunce and Forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, as of the partes thereof.<note n="x" place="margin">What follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</note> And therefore here followeth a moſt wholeſome doctrine of Repentance &amp; forgiuenes of ſinnes.<note n="*" place="margin">The 13. cha.</note> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">From the 1. ver. vnto the 6.</note> He exhorteth vs to repentance by examples,<note n="z" place="margin">From the 6 ver. vnto the 10</note> and by a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſimilitude of a figge tree, teaching what lighteth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the impenite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,<note n="a" place="margin">From the 10 ver. vnto the 14.</note> &amp; what be the fruits of true repentance,<note n="b" place="margin">From the 14 ver. vnto the 18</note> &amp; what the corrupt fruits of falſe repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce:<note n="c" place="margin">From the 18 ver vnto the 23</note> He ſheweth moreouer from whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce the power
<pb facs="tcp:19465:48"/> to bring forth the fruites of repentaunce &amp; to doe good works is.<note n="d" place="margin">From the 23 verſe vnto the end of the chap.</note> Forthwith he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horteth vs all, that we would indeuour to enter through the ſtaight and harde way, which leadeth vnto life. For he diſputeth againe of that moſt famous two wayes, bringing in ſomewhat touching the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of the impenitent, and concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the equitie of the iudgementes of God, which deſtroyeth the incurable, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no faithfull dealing and diligence coulde heale.<note n="*" place="margin">The 14. cha.</note> Then hee taketh from the louers of godlineſſe errours &amp; certaine no light faultes, and teacheth them the dueties of godlineſſe.<note n="e" place="margin">From the 1 ver. vnto the 7.</note> For he remoueth againe the error of the Sabboths religious obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.<note n="f" place="margin">From the 7. ver. vnto the 12</note> He preſſeth downe the pride &amp; lof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Phariſees, &amp; graffeth in modeſt humilitie:<note n="g" place="margin">In the 12, 13 and 14. ver.</note> &amp; teacheth vs alſo bountiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.<note n="h" place="margin">From the 15 verſe vnto the 24.</note> Herevpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> taking occaſion by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crie of a certaine geſt, which pronounced him bleſſed, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> may eate breade in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God, he exhorteth al men to faith, leaſt they make them ſelues vnworthy the kingdom of god through vnbeliefe: where y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord ſetteth forth alſo the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel of God touching y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſauing of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſaith is deſpiſed of certaine through the deſire
<pb facs="tcp:19465:49"/> 
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:19465:49"/> 
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:19465:50"/> 
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:19465:50"/> 
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:19465:51"/> of thinges preſent,<note n="i" place="margin">In the 24. ver</note> vnto whome alſo he threatneth puniſhment. And theſe things hath he ſpoken of thoſe whiche hinder the calling of God:<note n="k" place="margin">Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the 25. verſe vnto the ende of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chap.</note> On the contrarie parte he oppoſeth the doctrine, how we ought to followe the Lord calling vs, &amp; to obey his calling: that is to ſay, of what ſort the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord ought to be, &amp; what they ought to promiſe to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel.<note n="*" place="margin">The 15 chap</note> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">From the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the chap. to the end.</note> vnto theſe things he knitteth certaine moſt comely ſimilitudes, whereby he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth againe the reaſon of true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, yea and the reaſon of the forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſinnes chiefly, namely of the grace and vnmeaſurable mercie of God, reproo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing euery where the pride and hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie of<note n="*" place="margin">They may be called Iuſtitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, which hold that a man may be iuſtified by his own works.</note> Iuſtitiaries.<note n="*" place="margin">The 16. cha.</note> 
               <note n="m" place="margin">In the whole chapter.</note> After theſe things he reaſoneth plentifully of the duties of the faithfull, to witte, of charitie, and boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifulneſſe towardes our neighbours, to be breefe of the contempt of earthly thinges, againſt couetouſneſſe, in the behalfe of pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifulneſſe, &amp; of the vſe and abuſe of earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thinges. And all theſe thinges doeth he ſhadowe foorth, and as it were propoſe to be vewed with our eyes in the parables of the falſe ſtewarde, and of the rich glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,
<pb facs="tcp:19465:51"/> and of <hi>Lazarus</hi> the begger.<note n="*" place="margin">The 17. cha.</note>
               <note n="n" place="margin">The occaſion of that which followeth.</note> There be not a fewe wicked men, vnto whome, whatſoeuer is preached concerning hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and hell, ſeeme fables, and they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect ſucceſſiuely not a few with their poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned and blaſphemous tongues.<note n="o" place="margin">In the 1. and 2. verſes.</note> Our Lorde ſheweth therefore conſequently howe great their offence is before God.<note n="p" place="margin">In the 3. and 4. verſes.</note> Agayne he teacheth thee to forgiue treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes if any bee committed againſt thee.<note n="q" place="margin">In the 5. and 6. verſes.</note> The which thing becauſe it can not bee done without the help of faith, wholeſome doctrine touching faith is forthwith adioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.<note n="r" place="margin">From the 7 ver. vnto the 12</note> After the which he placeth ſtreight way doctrine touching the ſame, that wee aſcribe nothing vnto our ſelues, but yeeld all the glorie to the Lorde: who onely pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth vs, and giueth vs ſtrength to worke good workes, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which cauſe we ought to giue him great thankes.<note n="s" place="margin">From the 12 verſe vnto the 20.</note> And this point is ſet foorth, as it were to be vewed with our eyes, in the hiſtorie of the tenne leapers, which were cleanſed.<note n="t" place="margin">From the 20. ver. vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 26.</note> Now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is mention made very often times of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdome of God throughout all this hiſtorie, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter is handeled more plainly.<note n="v" place="margin">From the 26 ver. vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 31.</note> Then is it adioyned, what they
<pb facs="tcp:19465:52"/> ſhall ſuffer, which wil not beleeue that the kingdome of God is come.<note n="x" place="margin">From the 31 ver. vnto the end of the chap.</note> Moreouer it is ſhewed, what troubles and calamities ſhall come to paſſe in the worlde, euen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ende of the worlde, and howe the faithfull ought to beare them ſelues in the ſame.<note n="*" place="margin">The 18. cha.</note> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">From the firſt ver. vnto the 6</note> Where he exhorteth his <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples</hi> earneſtly to moſt feruent prayers,<note n="z" place="margin">In the 6.7. and 8 verſes.</note> promiſing that God alſo will auenge his <hi>elect.</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">From the 9. ver. vnto the 15</note> And becauſe there were many, which truſted in them ſelues, he propoſeth the parable of the Phariſee and the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licane, which went vp into the temple, and teacheth which is true righteouſnes, and howe men are iuſtified.<note n="b" place="margin">In the 15.16. &amp; 17. ver.</note> Which thinge being expounded, he inſtructeth vs, what we ſhould thinke of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of infants:<note n="c" place="margin">From the 18 verſe vnto the 23.</note> What good thing euery one ſhould doe, that hee may poſſeſſe the kingdome of God:<note n="d" place="margin">From the 23 ver. vnto the 28</note> howe hardly rich men enter into the kingdome of GOD:<note n="e" place="margin">In the 28, 29. &amp; 30 ver.</note> what inwarde is prepared for them, that leaue their worldly ſubſtance for the Lord his ſake:<note n="f" place="margin">From the 31 ver. vnto the 35</note> In the ſame place the Lorde ſheweth his <hi>diſciples</hi> what hee him ſelfe muſt ſuffer.<note n="g" place="margin">From the 35 verſe vnto the end of the chap.</note> Then followeth the hiſtorie of the blind man, which receiued his ſight,
<pb facs="tcp:19465:52"/> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">The 19. cha.</note> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">From the 1. verſe vnto the 11.</note> &amp; the calling of <hi>Zacheus</hi> that famous Publicane, and his receiuing into the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of Chriſt: whereby wee are taught, how all men are illuminated, receiued in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to fauour, and iuſtified, and what they, which are iuſtified, ſhoulde worke, or howe they ſhoulde behaue them ſelues towards God, and towardes their neighbours.<note n="i" place="margin">The occaſion of the parable following.</note> Our Lorde Ieſus executed the prieſt his office all the time of his diſpenſation, but chiefly in thoſe laſt dayes, wherein he ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly finiſhed our ſaluation by dying and ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing againe. Therefore the nearer hee commeth vnto the citie, the more plainely he declareth him ſelfe to bee the king and prieſt of God his people, and thorowely doth the office of the prieſt and king. And firſt, becauſe there were ſome eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> among his owne <hi>diſciples,</hi> which ſuppoſed that the kingdome of Chriſt ſhould be earthly, and that it ſhoulde riſe vp forthwith, the Lorde taketh away this errour,<note n="k" place="margin">Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the 11. verſe vnto the 28.</note> and teacheth by a ſimilitude what maner of kingdome the <hi>kingdome</hi> of Chriſte is, and when it ſhall come.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="l" place="margin">From the 28 ver. vnto the 41</note>Foorthwith ſitting vppon an Aſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:19465:53"/> and being caried into the citie, hee decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth by that his glorious comming, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it were humble, that he is that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected king of the people of God.<note n="m" place="margin">From the 41 ver. vnto the 45</note> And yet before he entereth into <hi>the citie</hi> he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayleth with teares the deſtenies and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities of the blinde citie, which hee fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheweth moſt plainely, and declareth the cauſe of the calamities.<note n="n" place="margin">From the 45 ver. vnto the end of the chapter.</note> And becauſe it is the duetie of a king, to reſtore decaies, and to reforme corruptions, beyng en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the Temple, hee caſteth out the buyers and ſellers, and hee him ſelfe preacheth dayly in the Temple.<note n="*" place="margin">The 20 chap</note> 
               <note n="o" place="margin">From the 1. ver. vnto the 9.</note> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſked of the Prieſtes by whome hee was authoriſed a King and a Prieſt? hee ſheweth that hee hath all his authoritie from God foorth of heauen.<note n="p" place="margin">From the 9. verſe vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 19</note> Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer hee rebuketh moſt grauely the rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions, by bringing in the parable of the vineyarde and of the huſbandemen, ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowing foorth the meane while the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, whiche hanged ouer them, for their rebellion.<note n="q" place="margin">Where of he ſpeaketh in the reſt of the chap.</note> To bee breefe, forſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as it belongeth to the Prieſt his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to teache the people of GOD, and to confute the gayne-ſayers, <hi>Luke</hi> pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth
<pb facs="tcp:19465:53"/> after theſe thinges certayne diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and familiar ſpeaches of the Lorde had with his aduerſaries.<note n="r" place="margin">Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the 19. ver. vnto the 27</note> And firſt hee teacheth what wee owe to God, and what to the Magiſtrate.<note n="ſ" place="margin">From the 27 verſe vnto the 41.</note> Then he reaſoneth of the hope of the Saintes, and what ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of life is in the worlde to come.<note n="t" place="margin">From the 41 ver. vnto the 45</note> Thirdly, hee ſheweth what onely is to bee looked for in all the Scriptures, namely Chriſt true GOD and man the ſauiour of the world.<note n="v" place="margin">From the 45 ver. vnto the end of the chapter.</note> Which thinges being fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed the Lorde paynteth foorth, in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of his prieſtly office, counterfayte prieſtes, of whoſe corruption hee diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly admoniſheth his <hi>diſciples</hi> to beware, and to auoyde.<note n="*" place="margin">The 21. cha.</note> 
               <note n="x" place="margin">From the firſt ver. vnto the 5.</note> Afterwarde he allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the widowes gift caſt into the treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in the temple.<note n="y" place="margin">From the 5. ver. vnto the 25</note> Where he taketh oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to intreate moſt plentifully of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the citie &amp; nation of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes.<note n="z" place="margin">From the 25. ver. vnto the 34</note> From that deſtruction he commeth to the deſtruction alſo of all the world, and to the ende of the worlde, and to be briefe defineth &amp; pointeth forth the ſignes going next before the laſt day.<note n="a" place="margin">From the 34. verſe vnto the ende of the chapter.</note> Where he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horteth moſt dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faithful to watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes &amp; ſobernes, leaſt they be ouerthowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:19465:54"/> of a ſodaine with the vnfaythfull, &amp; periſh.<note n="*" place="margin">The 22. chap</note> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">What went before &amp; what foloweth.</note> The Lorde hath hetherto fulfilled all the prieſtlike functions euen vnto the kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and offering vp of the ſacrifice, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the expiatorie and purging ſacrifice only remained to be accompliſhed: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Luke</hi> will deſcribe by thoſe thinges, which followe, the paſſion and death of the Lorde, which is the onely and wholeſome oblation once offred for the ſinnes of al the worlde.<note n="c" place="margin">In the 1. ver.</note> And firſt he noteth the time,<note n="d" place="margin">From the 2, ver. vnto the 7</note> then he ſheweth the cauſes of his death:<note n="e" place="margin">From the 7. ver. vnto the 17</note> herevpon he toucheth how he celebrated y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paſſeouer:<note n="f" place="margin">From the 17 vnto the 21.</note> after which he placeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie inſtitution of his myſticall ſupper.<note n="g" place="margin">In the 21.22 &amp; 23 ver.</note> He addeth, what the Lorde ſpake of him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> betrayed him:<note n="h" place="margin">From the 23 ver. vnto the 31</note> &amp; how he quieted the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſciples, rayſed touching this, which of them ſeemed greateſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God.<note n="i" place="margin">From the 31 ver. vnto the 35</note> He foreſheweth the earneſt purpoſe of the diuell againſt all the diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, &amp; namely againſt <hi>Peter</hi> the denier.<note n="k" place="margin">From the 35 verſe vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 39</note> Forthwith he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeth them to prouide them ſwords:<note n="l" place="margin">In the 39. and 41. ver.</note> &amp; taking his diſciples vnto him, he goeth out with his choſen vnto the mount of <hi>Oliues.</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">In the 41. and 42 verſes.</note> Here he prayeth vnto the father moſt feruently.<note n="n" place="margin">From the 43 ver. vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 47</note> There he is
<pb facs="tcp:19465:54"/> torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted with an agonie, which wringeth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him a bloody ſweat. He receiueth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of an angell.<note n="o" place="margin">In the 47. and 48 verſes.</note> After this he is take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; bounden by the prieſts ſeruants:<note n="p" place="margin">In the 49. and 50 verſes.</note> which when <hi>Peter</hi> would haue withſtood, he cut off the prieſt his ſeruant his eare:<note n="q" place="margin">In the 51. verſe.</note> but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord healeth him being wounded,<note n="r" place="margin">In the 52 and 53. verſes.</note> and moſt ſharply rebuketh them which tooke him.<note n="s" place="margin">In the 54 ver</note> Moreouer being taken he is led in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the citie, &amp; brought before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> high prieſt.<note n="t" place="margin">From the 55. ver. vnto 63</note> Then did <hi>Peter</hi> ſhamefully deny y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord &amp; that not once.<note n="v" place="margin">In the 63.64. &amp; 65 ver.</note> The ſeruants of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> high prieſts &amp; of wickednes mocke the Lord al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all the night long, &amp; abuſe him moſt vnworthily.<note n="x" place="margin">From the 66. ver. vnto the end of the chapter.</note> Earely in the morning he is condemned by the ſenate of the prieſts &amp; of the chiefe of <hi>Hieruſalem.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">The 23 cha.</note> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">In the 1. ver.</note> Being co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned he is deliuered to <hi>Pilate,</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">From the 2. ver. vnto the 6.</note> cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne pointes of accuſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being propoſed forthwith <hi>againſt him.</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">In the 6. &amp; 7. verſes.</note> 
               <hi>Pilate</hi> willing to gratifie <hi>Herode,</hi> ſendeth the Lorde away vnto him.<note n="b" place="margin">From the 8. ver. vnto the 13</note> But he ſendeth him back be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing notably mocked and clothed with a white garment, to <hi>Pilate.</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the 13. ver. vnto the 26</note> He, after much reaſoning had with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes, &amp; after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had looſed <hi>Barrabbas,</hi> deliuered Ieſus to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miniſters of wickednes do be crucified.
<pb facs="tcp:19465:55"/> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">In the 26. ver</note> Therefore is he led away forthwith be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing innocent, bearing his croſſe, &amp; behinde him one <hi>Simon</hi> following him, and ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vp the ſame croſſe.<note n="e" place="margin">In the 27. verſe.</note> Certaine godly women lament his moſt bitter caſe.<note n="f" place="margin">From the 28. ver. vnto the 32</note> But the Lorde, this occaſion beyng offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, commaundeth them to lament their owne calamitie, whiche hee foreſheweth ſhall come vpon the citie and people.<note n="g" place="margin">In the 32. &amp; 33. verſes.</note> The meane while hee commeth into the place of execution, where hee being cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied is lift vp in the middeſt betweene two theeues.<note n="h" place="margin">From the 34 ver. vnto the 40</note> There hee firſt prayeth, and then ſuffering many reproches, hee dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth all thinges paciently.<note n="i" place="margin">From the 40 ver. vnto the 44</note> Among other things, he receiueth one of the thee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, whiche made ſupplication vnto him, into the felowſhip and partaking of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life, declaring by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple, how great the force of the ſacrifice once offered is.<note n="k" place="margin">In the 44.45 &amp; 46 verſes</note> After this certaine wonders followed te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifiyng, that the Sonne of God ſuffered. The Lord commending his ſpirit to God the father gaue vp the ghoſt vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe.<note n="l" place="margin">In the 47. ver</note> The Centurion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Romane ſouldiers being moued w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the wonders, &amp; touched w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; death of Chriſt, doth witnes that he was a iuſt man.<note n="m" place="margin">In the 48. &amp; 49. verſes.</note> The Lord his
<pb facs="tcp:19465:55"/> acquaintaunce ſee all theſe thinges, God his prouidence no doubt ſo ordering the matter, that they might be ſeeing wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, appointed for ſo great thinges.<note n="n" place="margin">From the 50. ver. vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 55.</note> Laſtly <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> a moſt famous Senatour of the citie, commeth vnto <hi>Pilate,</hi> and beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the body of the Lorde, that he might burie it: which when he had obtained and taken it downe from the tree, hee laid it in the graue, and buried it gloriouſly.<note n="o" place="margin">In the 55. &amp; 56. verſes.</note> Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine women behelde and marked it, that they might come the next day following to annoynt the body.<note n="*" place="margin">The 24. cha.</note> 
               <note n="p" place="margin">What follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</note> Ieſus Chriſt our King &amp; Prieſt, hauing purged ſinne, conquered hell, and ouercome death, reſtored to life foorth of the graue &amp; from the dead, the third day, riſeth againe a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querer and a triumphant Lorde. And becauſe the whole matter of our hope and life ſtandeth in the liuely reſurrection of our Lorde Ieſus, it is prooued by euident ſignes and arguments.<note n="q" place="margin">From the firſt ver. vnto 12.</note> And firſt the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of our Lord is declared by the very Angels of God to certaine deuout women, which came to annoynt the body of our Lorde Ieſus.<note n="r" place="margin">In the 12 verſe.</note> Foorthwith the ſame is made knowen to <hi>Peter</hi> by cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſignes.<note n="ſ" place="margin">From the 13. ver. vnto the 36</note> Afterwardes, as two of
<pb facs="tcp:19465:56"/> the Diſciples were going to <hi>Emaus,</hi> the Lorde ioyneth him ſelfe vnto them in the fourme of a ſtranger, and proueth vnto them moſt plainely, as well foorth of the Scriptures, as by the thing it ſelfe, that he was riſen againe from the dead.<note n="t" place="margin">From the 36. ver. vnto the 44</note> Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the Lord commeth in the middeſt of his Diſciples, and ſheweth to the viewe of eye his true and liuely reſurrection.<note n="v" place="margin">In the 44.45 and 46. verſes.</note> Moreouer hee confirmeth their mindes with the Scriptures.<note n="x" place="margin">In the 47. &amp; 48. verſes.</note> And that wee might all vnderſtand, that all Chriſte his things are ours, he commaundeth his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples to preach the Goſpel to all nations,<note n="y" place="margin">In the 49. verſe.</note> for the accompliſhing wherof he promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth them the holy Ghoſt, whom hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth them to looke for in the Citie of <hi>Hieruſalem.</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">In the 50. verſe.</note> All the which things bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing done in deed, he leadeth his diſciples foorth to the mount of <hi>Oliues,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">In the 51. verſe.</note> from thence he aſcendeth ſtraight into heauen.<note n="b" place="margin">In the 52. &amp; 53. verſes.</note> The diſciples hauing worſhipped him, returne into the Citie looking for the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt.</p>
            <trailer>Heere endeth the ſumme of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell by Saint Luke.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="John" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:19465:56"/>
            <head>¶The ſumme of the <hi>Goſpell by Saint Iohn.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hey,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The</hi> 1. <hi>chap.</hi> The reaſon of the entrance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Goſpel by Iohn.</note> which will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound any thing by cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine reaſon and with great profite, place be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their expoſition a propoſition, a marke, or a Summe of the whole matter to bee expounded, vnto the which the auditours bending the ſharpeneſſe of wit, and all their vnderſtanding, may knowe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto all things tende, which are ſpoken, and what the vſe of them is.<note n="b" place="margin">What Iohn handeleth in his Goſpell.</note> 
               <hi>Iohn</hi> the Apoſtle therefore about to expounde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matters of Chriſt the Lorde, that is to ſay, his wordes and deedes, and all the myſterie of our redemption, placeth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his hiſtorical narration a propoſition, plentifully opened, &amp; containing in effect theſe things.<note n="c" place="margin">In the 1. and 2. verſes.</note> The word of God, that is to ſay, the ſonne of God, Ieſus Chriſt our Lorde, of whom I minde to ſpeake, was
<pb facs="tcp:19465:57"/> with God from euerlaſting, and is very God,<note n="d" place="margin">In the 3. ver.</note> by whom all thinges were made,<note n="e" place="margin">In the 4.5.7 and 8. verſes.</note> the ſame by his owne nature is the life &amp; the light.<note n="f" place="margin">In the 9. ver.</note> And becauſe wee, by our humane nature, and through the fault of ſinne, bee darkeneſſe &amp; the ſlaues of death, the worde, or ſonne of God deſcended fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen, came into the world, was incarnat and made man, that through his life and light, the <hi>Iewes</hi> chiefly, vnto whome the <hi>Mesſias</hi> was peculiarly promiſed, might liue and bee illuminated.<note n="g" place="margin">In the 10. &amp; 11. verſes.</note> But becauſe they caſt him off, not beeing wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to beleeue the life and light giuen them,<note n="h" place="margin">In the 12.13 &amp; 14. verſes.</note> therefore he gaue power to all men which receiue Chriſte with a true faith, of what nation, ſexe, age, or conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they be, to become the ſonnes of God, that is to ſay, heires of life and of all heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly good things, and the very fellow heires of Chriſt, which is the truth, the grace, the redemption, and the fulneſſe, or the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummation of all beleeuers, in whom on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the faithfull haue all thinges, which do pertaine to godlineſſe and life.<note n="i" place="margin">The ſumme of the Goſpell.</note> This is the ſumme of all the narration of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell: Namely, that through faith in
<pb facs="tcp:19465:57"/> Chriſte our ſinnes bee forgiuen, and that euerlaſting life is beſtowed vpon vs.<note n="k" place="margin">In the 6. ver. and from the 15 vnto the 19.</note> Vnto this head <hi>Iohn</hi> coupleth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very body of the Euangelicall narration or hiſtorie, beginning his hiſtorie at the preaching &amp; teſtimonie of <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt, as alſo the other three Euangeliſtes did.<note n="l" place="margin">From the 19. ver. vnto the 35</note> And hee teacheth of what maner were his teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, priuate, publike, and giuen to the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie meſſengers of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> all verely of one kinde, namely ſuch as taught, that Ieſus Chriſt is true God and man, ſente into the worlde for ſinners, to ſaue them which beleeue <hi>in him,</hi> &amp; that therefore we muſt beleeue in Chriſt.<note n="m" place="margin">In the 35.36. &amp; 37. ver.</note> Therefore doth he alſo ſend his Diſciples vnto him, and conſecrateth them to Chriſt the Lord, ſhewing vndoubtedly by the very deede it ſelfe, that all his doctrine tendeth here vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, that wee may beleeue Chriſt the onely Sauiour of all the world.<note n="n" place="margin">Why the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſt briefly finiſheth the hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of the Bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſt, and ſpeedily commeth to the hiſtory of Chriſte him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</note> And becauſe the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> preached Chriſt only, &amp; in him only ſheweth all the points of godlineſſe &amp; life, paſſing ouer the matters of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Baptiſt, Iohn</hi> the Euangeliſte maketh haſt to deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribe the very matters of Chriſt,<note n="o" place="margin">The 38.39 and 40 verſes.</note> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth firſt how he receiued them, which
<pb facs="tcp:19465:58"/> by the prouocation of <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed him:<note n="p" place="margin">In the 41. ver</note> alſo what the ſtudies and workes of the faithfull be, namely to bring very many vnto Chriſt.<note n="q" place="margin">From the 42. verſ. vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 51.</note> There is briefly handeled the calling of certaine of the diſciples, in whoſe examples we may learne, how men are called to the faith of the Goſpell, and what maner of men they ought to bee, which muſt bee inſtructed in the doctrine of the Goſpell.<note n="r" place="margin">In the laſt verſe.</note> The Lorde inſtructeth his Diſciples by words and ſignes. By plaine wordes, witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that hee is to them, which beleeue, the ladder and gate to a bleſſed life.<note n="*" place="margin">The 2 chap.</note> 
               <note n="x" place="margin">From the firſt ver. vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 13.</note> Furthermore hee ſheweth a worthie ſigne at a marriage, turning water into wine, that by that deede hee might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare his power, that it is hee, which by his woorde can doe what hee will, that they may boldly leane vnto him, which truſt in him. And theſe thinges did hee as it were priuately amongſt his acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and familiar <hi>freendes.</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">From the 13 ver. vnto the 18.</note> But hee came not to be made knowen in ſome one place only to a fewe, but in all <hi>Iurie,</hi> yea and to all the worlde, therefore hee goeth to <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> the chiefe citie and
<pb facs="tcp:19465:58"/> head of the countrey, and maketh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe knowen to all men by a very great deede, and very fit for his purpoſe. For whereas hee was come into the worlde the king, and Prieſt, and <hi>Mesſias</hi> of all the faithfull in the worlde, and becauſe it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertained to the <hi>Mesſias</hi> to purge religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from corruption, and to deliuer his from tyrannie and ſuperſtition, hee went ſtraight wayes into the holy temple, and caſt foorth of it the buyers &amp; ſellers, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging religion, and ſo ſhewing himſelfe to bee the expected <hi>Mesſias.</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">In the 18. ver<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> But the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tooke this thing very gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly, requiring a ſigne, whereby hee might proue, that he was hee, whome hee tooke vpon him to be.<note n="a" place="margin">From the 19. ver. vnto the 22</note> Hee reaſoneth of his death and reſurrection, although ſomewhat cloſely.<note n="b" place="margin">In the 22 ver</note> And not a fewe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued the Lorde,<note n="c" place="margin">In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 23. ver.</note> but ſome againe clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked their faith, following rather y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> corrupt affection of their minde, than the motion of the holy Ghoſt,<note n="d" place="margin">In the 24. &amp; 25. verſes</note> vnto whom the Lord would not therefore commit himſelfe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee was not ignorant of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels and cogitations of their heartes, and kept himſelfe for better affayres.
<pb facs="tcp:19465:59"/> Theſe thinges are handeled in the two firſt Chapters.<note n="e" place="margin">What the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſt trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth of.</note> The Apoſtle doth dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently handle thoſe thinges, which the Lorde Ieſus ſpake and did in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his preaching, that he might ſo rightly informe the iudgemente of the Church, to think very wel of Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, &amp; of the principles therof, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which, as els where often, ſo here alſo, are wont for the moſt part to bee very harde.<note n="f" place="margin">What went before.</note> Hee ſhewed laſt before, what Ieſus did pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely and openly in the temple of God, and what he reaſoned of among the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people, what hee ſpake and did,<note n="g" place="margin">What follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</note> and now wil he ſhew a certaine priuate thing.<note n="*" place="margin">The 3. chap.</note> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">In the 1, 2. &amp; 3. verſes.</note> For the Lord vſeth priuate conference with <hi>Nicodemus</hi> a Doctour of the Law,<note n="i" place="margin">The ſumme of the Lord his talke with Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>codemus.</note> whom he inſtructeth ſoundly, fully, and ſimply in the foundation, as they call it, and in the firſt principles, knitting toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the whole method of ſincere doctrin, and<note n="k" place="margin">In the 3. verſe.</note> teaching, that he, which deſireth to enter into the kingdome of God, muſt needes firſt be borne anewe. Becauſe our nature and our firſt natiuitie hath in it ſelf no light or life.<note n="l" place="margin">From the 4, ver. vnto the 13</note> Moreouer y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this new birth conſiſteth in the renouation of the
<pb facs="tcp:19465:59"/> holy Ghoſt, by whoſe meanes he which is to be ſaued knoweth, that there is nothing in the ſtrength of man, which can deſerue iuſtification and bleſſed life,<note n="m" place="margin">In the 13, 14, &amp; 15. ver.</note> that thoſe things are prouided by an others deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, namely by Ieſus Chriſt,<note n="n" place="margin">In the 16. verſe.</note> whom the grace &amp; loue of God, &amp; no deſert of ours, gaue vnto vs, yea and gaue him to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt ſhamefull death of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe, that euery one, which beleeueth in him, ſhould not periſh, but ſhould haue euerlaſting life.<note n="o" place="margin">From the 17. ver. vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 22.</note> There he teacheth that true faith in Chriſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth good woorkes: and contrarily that incredulitie and want of faith is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe of all vngodlineſſe, yea of damnation it ſelfe.<note n="p" place="margin">From the 22 verſe vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 26</note> Theſe things being finiſhed, the Apoſtle handeleth forthwith the queſtion touching purifying, ſprong vp after the matters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore goyng.<note n="q" place="margin">From the 27 verſ. vnto the end of the chap.</note> By occaſion whereof hee reporteth the fift and moſt plaine teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt, whereby hee wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth, that the faithfull are fully purged through the grace of Chriſt. And that he is the true <hi>Meſſias,</hi> in whom the Father hath giuen to the world, whatſoeuer appertay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to true ſaluation, and that therefore they which beleeue in Chriſt are ſaued, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:19465:60"/> contrarily that they which beleeue not are damned.<note n="r" place="margin">What follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</note> Vnto theſe things he knitteth, by a marueilous &amp; a moſt wiſe deuiſe, an other, and a new conference, and the ſame priuate alſo, betweene the Lorde and a woman of <hi>Samaria.</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">What went before.</note> He receiued and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in the third chapter <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> a famous man, a Iewe, learned, and a man of holineſſe not to be deſpiſed:<note n="t" place="margin">The matter co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tained in the 4. chap.</note> but now he receiueth &amp; inſtructeth an obſcure woman, a Gentile, vnlearned, and verye greately defiled with heynous faultes, to this ende, leaſt any ſhoulde gather by the former example, that the Lorde came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the worlde to ſaue the godlie onelie. For hereby we do vnderſtand, that he was borne to ſaue ſinners alſo, and that not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Iewes, but the Gentiles alſo, yea and the very <hi>Samaritanes.</hi> The confere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce hath in it much pleaſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tneſſe &amp; ſweetneſſe. The Lorde inſinuateth himſelfe into the minde of the ſinfull woman merueilouſly: notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding he goeth about 2. thinges chiefly.<note n="*" place="margin">The 4. chap.</note> 
               <note n="v" place="margin">From the 1. ver vnto the 20</note> Firſt he ſheweth, that he is the fountayne of goodneſſe, and of all gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, of the whiche whoſoeuer drinke, may bee moſte plentifully ſatiſfied.<note n="x" place="margin">In the 20.21, and 22, verſes.</note> Then
<pb facs="tcp:19465:60"/> hauing confuted the falſe woorſhipping of GOD,<note n="y" place="margin">In the 23. and 24, verſes.</note> hee teacheth which is the true woorſhipping:<note n="z" place="margin">In the 15, 26 &amp; 27. verſes.</note> and therewithall he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth by a moſt manifeſt confeſſion, that hee is the true <hi>Meſſias.</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">In the 28, 29, &amp; 30. ver.</note> Foorthwith the ſinfull woman becommeth a preacher of the grace of GOD. For ſhee calleth foorth the <hi>Sycharenes</hi> or <hi>Sychimites</hi> to meete the Lorde the king or the <hi>Meſſias.</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">From the 31 ver vnto the 39</note> The meane while the Lord diſputeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong his diſciples of the calling of the Gentiles &amp; of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtleſhip to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiles.<note n="c" place="margin">From the 39. ver vnto the 43</note> Verily the <hi>Samaritanes</hi> receiue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord.<note n="d" place="margin">In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 43, 44, &amp; 45. verſes.</note> But the Iewes, eſpecially y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> citize<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> towne of <hi>Nazareth,</hi> do deſpiſe &amp; caſt him off:<note n="d" place="margin">From the 46 ver. vnto the end of the chapter.</note> Wherwith the Lord is ſo little offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is nothing at all leſſe bountifull vnto the euill deſeruing Iewes. For go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Cana a citie of Galilee,</hi> he reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to health the ſeruant of a certayne ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler beeing at the very poynt of death, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing by that woorthie deede, that hee can ſaue their life, whiche put their truſt in him, beeyng the authour of life and of all goodneſſe.<note n="e" place="margin">What went before.</note> The notable inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and diſputations of Chriſt the Lord in true Chriſtian religion hitherto had
<pb facs="tcp:19465:61"/> with <hi>Nicodemus</hi> and the woman of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria,</hi> were as it were priuate.<note n="f" place="margin">What follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</note> In the two next chapters follow publike bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites of the ſame Chriſt our Lorde, which miniſter occaſion of publike diſputations, verye notable, the which diſputations doe handle the ſame, that is to ſay, the greateſt pointes of our faith.<note n="*" place="margin">The 5. cha.</note> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">From the 1 ver. vnto the 10</note> The one benefite he doeth to a man beyng pitifully afflicted many yeres with a moſt greeuous diſeaſe, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he healeth moſt louingly.<note n="h" place="margin">From the 10 ver. vnto the 17</note> But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had done this vpon the Sabboth day, the Phariſees ſclaunder the benefite, and accuſe the benefactor of breaking the ſabboth.<note n="i" place="margin">In the 17. ver</note> The Lorde defending his owne cauſe, ſheweth, as it were by the example of his father the eternal God, that he brake not the Sabboth.<note n="k" place="margin">In the 18. ver.</note> Forth of the which an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere they pike a new matter of accuſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> laying vnto the Lorde his charge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> crime of treaſon againſt God, and of blaſphemie againſt God.<note n="l" place="margin">From the 19. ver. vnto the 40</note> Whervpon he prooueth by many, and the ſame moſt liuely and moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident arguments, that God is his father, and that he is the ſonne of God by nature, and equall with the father in all things, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the true, the liuing, and eternall God.
<pb facs="tcp:19465:61"/> 
               <note n="m" place="margin">From the 40. verſe vnto the 44.</note> Notwithſtanding in the end of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration he falleth to chide or to expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtulate the matter with the Iewes,<note n="n" place="margin">In the 44 verſe.</note> and he openeth the cauſes of mans infidelitie and treacherie, namely the deſire of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, of riches, and of pleaſure,<note n="o" place="margin">In the 45, 46, &amp; 47 ver.</note> ioyning hereunto fearefull threatninges, that God the reuenger will once vndoubtedly moſt ſharpely puniſhe them.<note n="*" place="margin">The 6. chap.</note> 
               <note n="p" place="margin">From the 1. ver. vnto the 14</note> The other be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite is moſt publike. For hee maketh a marueilous, and a verie kinglike feaſt, vnto certayne thouſandes of men in the wilderneſſe, declaring thereby moſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly, that he is that ſonne to be honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of the bleſſed GOD, by whoſe ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and prouidence all liuing thinges are fedde and nouriſhed.<note n="q" place="margin">In the 14. verſe.</note> Nowe the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple not vnderſtanding the iuſt ende of ſo great a benefite, according to their groſſeneſſe, are willing to create the Lorde the king of Iſrael.<note n="r" place="margin">In the 15. ver</note> But the Lorde, whiche was not come to raigne in humilitie, vppon the earth, or in the countreye of the Iewes onelie, or to receiue a kingdome of men, but to bee a king, crowned by GOD the Father him ſelfe, glorious, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlye,
<pb facs="tcp:19465:62"/> in heauen and in all the earth together, and of all creatures viſible and inuiſible, departeth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth him ſelfe in a mountayne alone.<note n="ſ" place="margin">In the 16, 17 and 18. ver.</note> The diſciples, not knowing where the Lorde laye hidde, or whether hee was fledde, goe by ſhippe to <hi>Capernaum:</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">In the 19. ver.</note> Whom the Lorde following walked vppon the waues of the Sea, as vppon the mayne lande,<note n="v" place="margin">In the 20, 21. ver.</note> and holpe them being in perill in the lake,<note n="x" place="margin">The vſe of the myracle.</note> ſetting foorth vnto them by this proofe his diuine power.<note n="y" place="margin">In the 22, 23 &amp; 24. ver.</note> The nexte day the common people fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe him alſo in ſhippes,<note n="z" place="margin">In the 25. verſe.</note> miniſtring occaſion vnto him by their woordes, to reaſon openlie in the ſchoole of <hi>Caperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um</hi> touching the abridgement and ſumme of our religion,<note n="a" place="margin">From the 26 ver vnto the 30</note> namelie that hee is the true ſonne of GOD, ſent downe from heauen from the father, to giue life vnto al mankinde, and to conſerue them in life, in that hee was incarnate for vs, in that hee offered his fleſhe and his blood vnto the death for vs, that euery one, whiche beleeueth in him, maye haue life euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting.<note n="b" place="margin">From the 30 ver. vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 34</note> And hee propoſeth this chiefe myſterye of our faith by the continuall
<pb facs="tcp:19465:62"/> ſimilitude of bread or meate, and of drinke, of eating and alſo of drinking, beeyng hidde in an allegorie, that both ſpirituall thinges might more rightlye bee conceiued by the ſimilitude of bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thinges, and alſo that they might the more firmely ſticke in the mindes of men.<note n="c" place="margin">In the 34 verſe.</note> But when as the <hi>Capernaites</hi> vnderſtood theſe thinges the wrong way and groſſely,<note n="d" place="margin">From the 35. ver. vnto the 66.</note> the Lorde expoundeth him ſelfe moſte clearely, declaring plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, what hee meant by that kynde of ſpeache.<note n="e" place="margin">In the 66. verſe.</note> And when as not a fewe forſooke him,<note n="f" place="margin">In the 67. verſe.</note> hee aſketh thoſe his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, whom hee had called to the office of Apoſtleſhippe, whether they alſo pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to forſake him.<note n="g" place="margin">From the 68 ver. vnto the end of the chapter.</note> But bleſſed <hi>Peter</hi> in the behalfe of all the Apoſtles made a right confeſſion in all poyntes, and comprehending all the ſumme of a true fayth, leauing it to the Churche, that ſhee alſo in all troubles and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies maye ſo goe on to confeſſe Chriſt.<note n="h" place="margin">A briefe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſall of the ſumme of the 2. laſt chap.</note> Thou haſt therefore in theſe two laſt chapters, two miracles, the thirde and fourth, whiche Ieſus did, and whiche <hi>Iohn</hi> hath deſcribed: alſo
<pb facs="tcp:19465:63"/> two chiefe poyntes of our faith, moſte copiouſly and learnedly handeled, both that Ieſus is true GOD, of one ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce with the Father, and alſo that the ſame <hi>Ieſus</hi> is true man, the foode of the ſoule, and the conſeruation and life of euerye parte of euerie man whiche truſteth in him with a true faith.<note n="i" place="margin">What went before.</note> 
               <hi>Iohn</hi> hath hitherto plainely ſette foorth the abridgement, ſumme, and ſcope of all the doctrine of the Goſpell,<note n="k" place="margin">What follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</note> and nowe doeth hee ioyne heereunto cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne peculiar poyntes touching the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine and doctors of the Goſpell,<note n="*" place="margin">The 7. chap.</note> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">From the 1. ver. vnto the 14</note> What their duetie is:<note n="m" place="margin">In the 14, 15, &amp; 16. verſ.</note> what their doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine ought to bee:<note n="n" place="margin">In the 17, and 18. ver.</note> how doctrines may bee prooued and knowen, whether they bee of GOD:<note n="o" place="margin">From the 19 ver. vnto the 25</note> that Chriſt the Lorde committed none offence againſt the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the lawe:<note n="p" place="margin">In the 25, 26 &amp; 27. verſes.</note> alſo howe the doctrine of the trueth beeyng publiſhed is receiued of the worlde, and howe great troubles are rayſed for the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, whileſt the worlde goeth about to oppreſſe and cut of the Goſpell, by hands, by threatninges, and by murder.<note n="q" place="margin">From the 28. ver. vnto the 33</note> And yet in theſe troubles the Lorde goeth on
<pb facs="tcp:19465:63"/> notwithſtanding with a bolde courage, bearing witneſſe with the trueth,<note n="r" place="margin">From the 33 ver. vnto the 37</note> admoniſhing alſo what euilles are kept in ſtore for the deſpiſers of the Goſpel,<note n="ſ" place="margin">In the 37, 38, and 39, verſes.</note> and inculcating the ſame kynde of doctrine continuallye, to witte, from whence ſaluation commeth, euen from the onelye Sonne of GOD, if wee beleeue in him, and what the force of faith is.<note n="t" place="margin">In the 40, &amp; 41. verſes.</note> As the godlye doe with greate deſire receyue and imbrace this doctrine,<note n="v" place="margin">In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 41, 42, &amp; 43. verſes.</note> ſo are the wicked more and more incenſed thereby, indeuouring with tauntes to deface it, and by all meanes to oppreſſe it,<note n="x" place="margin">From the 44 ver. vnto the end of the chapter.</note> but the power of God is not ouercome of the weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of men, whiche <hi>without GOD</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes commeth to nothing, and vaniſheth awaye mocked and ſhamefully confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.<note n="*" place="margin">The 8. chap.</note> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">From the 1 ver. vnto the 12</note> After theſe thinges <hi>Iohn</hi> put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth downe a notable example of the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and mercie of GOD, whereby we maye vnderſtande, howe Ieſus is the fountayne of the water of life, watering the thirſtie to euerlaſting life.<note n="z" place="margin">In the 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. ver.</note> Againe vnder the couer of a certayne other ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude, comprehending the ſumme of ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d
<pb facs="tcp:19465:64"/> doctrine, hee teacheth, that hee is the light and Sauiour of all the worlde:<note n="a" place="margin">In the 13, 19 22, &amp; 25. ver.</note> whiche doctrine of the truth the braw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Iewes indeuouring to pollute, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill muche.<note n="b" place="margin">From the 14 ver. vnto the 31</note> But the Lorde doeth maynetayne and confirme the ſayde do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine grauely and firmely,<note n="c" place="margin">In the 21 vir</note> denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing puniſhment to the contentious,<note n="d" place="margin">In the 14, and 15 ver Alſo in the 19, and 22. ver.</note> opening with all the cauſes of contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and of errour,<note n="e" place="margin">From the 14. ver. vnto the 31</note> and declaring often times moſt clearely that hee is the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour of the worlde, whiche can ſaue them, that beleeue in him, and whiche can condemne them that beleeue not in him: that his doctrine is certayne, and infallible, the whiche by repeating often times hee doeth inculcate. For this muſt be retayned firmely in all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="f" place="margin">In the 31, &amp; 32. verſes.</note>Moreouer he inſtructeth more fully the faithfull and holy, whiche beleeued him, what they ſhoulde doe, howe they ought to continue in the knowen trueth, and what the freedome of the Sonnes of GOD is.<note n="g" place="margin">From the 33 ver. vnto the 48</note> Hee confuteth againe the wicked bragging of the Iewes, boaſting themſelues to bee the ſonnes of God, and
<pb facs="tcp:19465:64"/> the ſeede of <hi>Abraham.</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">In the 39 ver</note> For the Lord teacheth, who bee the true ſonnes of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">In the 42, &amp; 43. ver.</note> what the diſpoſition of the ſonnes of GOD,<note n="k" place="margin">In the 44, &amp; 45. verſ.</note> and of the Deuill is, alſo what the drift and woorkes of the deuill are,<note n="l" place="margin">In the 46, &amp; 47. verſes.</note> and that the hearing of God his woorde is the moſte euident marke of the Sonnes of GOD.<note n="m" place="margin">In the 48 ve</note> The Iewes receiue this faithfull and nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble diſputation of the Lorde with tauntes,<note n="n" place="margin">In the 49, 50, &amp; 51. ver.</note> vnto whome the Lorde propoſeth a newe the ſumme of the true and ſounde doctrine, namely that the ſaluation and the life of the worlde is not obtayned, but onely by fayth in Ieſus Chriſt,<note n="o" place="margin">From the 52 verſe vnto the 57.</note> yea and that <hi>Abraham</hi> him ſelfe liued by fayth in Ieſus Chriſt the Sonne of GOD.<note n="p" place="margin">From the 57 verſ. vnto the end of the chap.</note> At the whiche <hi>doctrine,</hi> as at ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame blaſphemye, they beeyng ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp, catche vp ſtones, to puniſhe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blaſphemer: but he withdrew him ſelfe forth of the troubleſome company.<note n="q" place="margin">A neceſſary point of doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine to be lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in theſe 2. chap.</note> Nowe this whole diſputation of theſe two chapters doe furniſhe vs with a moſte beautifull example of a thing moſte ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarye, namely howe wee ought in all troubles, perſecutions, threatnings, diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, bralles, reproches, and tauntes
<pb facs="tcp:19465:65"/> of this worlde, to haue an eye onelye to Chriſte, and to the infallible worde of his Goſpell, as to the onelye ſhippe-mans ſtarre in the tempeſtuous Sea, and to continue faithfull in him moſte conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.<note n="r" place="margin">What follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</note> The Apoſtle deſcribeth moſte plentifullye and moſte elegantly heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after the fifte miracle of the Lorde, or benefite beſtowed vpon a certayne blinde man.<note n="ſ" place="margin">The vſe of the myracle.</note> Whereby the Lorde Ieſus as by a liuely deede, confirmeth and declareth that, whiche hee lately pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to all the people in the temple, namely, that hee is the light of the world, whiche came to lighten and quicken all beleeuers.<note n="*" place="margin">The 9. chap.</note> 
               <note n="t" place="margin">From the 1. ver. vnto the 8.</note> For nowe by giuing ſight to him that was borne blinde, he ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth and prooueth manifeſtly by the thing it ſelfe, that hee is the giuer of light.<note n="v" place="margin">In the 39, 40, &amp; 41. verſ.</note> Yea a little before the ende of the hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorie, extending this his deede moſte largely to all men, hee addeth: <hi>I am come vnto iudgement in this worlde, that they whiche ſee not, might ſee: and that they whiche ſee, might bee made blinde:</hi> which is as it were the ſtate, where vnto wee maye referre the
<pb facs="tcp:19465:65"/> whole hiſtorie.<note n="x" place="margin">From the 8. ver. vnto the 35</note> The meane whyle, as vppon a certayne ſtage, is ſette foorth to the ſhewe, a ſharpe contention of the godly and vngodlye, about the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of religion, and the trueth of the confeſſion of the Goſpell.<note n="y" place="margin">In the 13, 15 16, 17, 18, 19, 24, 26, 28, 29 34, &amp; 40 verſ.</note> Heere are alſo paynted foorth the manners and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, not onely of the enimies of the woorde of GOD,<note n="z" place="margin">In the 9, 11, 12, 15, 17.20 25, 27, 30, 31, 32, &amp; 33, verſes.</note> but of ſimple Chriſtians alſo, whoſe duetie, francke confeſſion,<note n="a" place="margin">In the 36. &amp; 38. verſes</note> and increaſe of fayth are heere deſcribed.<note n="b" place="margin">The applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the hiſtorie before goyng.</note> Therefore thou ſhalt ſee, as in a certayne liuely picture, the counſels and indeauours of the wicked, whereby they perſecute the trueth, dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken it, and indeuour to oppreſſe it. Thou ſhalt ſee their maruellous ſlineſſe, their wrath, and enuie not to bee pacified, and their extreeme crueltie. Thou ſhalte ſee agayne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faithfulnes, ſimplicitie, ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, patience, conſtancie, and trueth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quering in all thinges, which alwayes ouercommeth by giuing place.<note n="*" place="margin">The 10. cha.</note>
               <note n="c" place="margin">From the 1. verſe vnto the 19.</note> After theſe thinges hee accuſeth great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie the blynde and vnfaithfull ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heardes of the people of the Iewes: and with all hee ſheweth, that hee is that
<pb facs="tcp:19465:66"/> true ſhephearde, whiche quickeneth his ſheepe with his death, redeemeth them by his power and care from all euilles, and refreſheth them with wholeſome foode. And in theſe thinges he ſetteth foorth the example of the beſt ſhephearde for all faithfull ſhepheardes, inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them what becommeth them, and what their duetie is: but chiefly hee inculcateth that, whiche hee vſeth to vrge euerye where, that hee is the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour of the worlde, whiche giueth life to the faithfull through his death.<note n="d" place="margin">In the 19, 20 &amp; 21. ver.</note> But there riſeth a newe buſineſſe and a newe diſſention about this doctrine, ſome wilfully cauellyng at the propoſed truth, and other no whitte the leſſe mayntay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and defending the ſame.<note n="e" place="margin">In the 22, 23, &amp; 24, ver.</note> In the feaſt of the dedication the aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries propoſe a queſtion to the Lorde, whereby they might take a newe occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to cauill. They demaunde: whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hee bee Chriſte, that bleſſed ſonne of almightie GOD, that is to ſay, the <hi>Meſſias?</hi> and if hee bee, that hee woulde confeſſe it openlye, plainely, and
<pb facs="tcp:19465:66"/> manifeſtly.<note n="f" place="margin">From the 25 ver. vnto the 31</note> Therefore the Lorde Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus profeſſeth, and not onelye profeſſeth, but alſo prooueth, that hee is Chriſte the bleſſed, the ſonne of the bleſſed God.<note n="g" place="margin">In the 31 ver.</note> By the whiche profeſſion they beeyng rather prouoked, then inſtructed, are willing to ſtone Ieſus as a blaſphemer.<note n="h" place="margin">From the 32 ver. vnto the 39</note> But hee reaſoning friendly with them, ſheweth that hee is the ſonne of GOD in deede, and that hee ſinned not at all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the maieſtie of his father.<note n="i" place="margin">In the 39, &amp; 40. verſ.</note> But becauſe no reaſons can preuayle with the groſſe, inflexible, and blinde aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, leauing them agayne, and paſſing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer Iordane, he returned vnto that place, where <hi>Iohn</hi> firſt beganne to baptiſe.<note n="k" place="margin">In the 41 ver</note> There he found not a few obedient ſheep.<note n="l" place="margin">In the laſt ver</note> For manie beleeued on Ieſus there.<note n="m" place="margin">What we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore &amp; what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</note> Hetherto wee haue hearde greate and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine thinges, and yet there follow after a ſorte greater and more diuine thinges,<note n="*" place="margin">The 11. cha.</note> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">From the 1. ver vnto the 46</note> and before all the reſt, the rayſing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne by Chriſte of <hi>Lazarus,</hi> hauing layne nowe foure dayes in the graue and ſtinking.<note n="o" place="margin">Why Chriſt wrought this myracle.</note> The laſt day of Chriſte the Lorde approched, wherein he offered
<pb facs="tcp:19465:67"/> him ſelfe, for the ſaluation of men, to GOD the father, to bee an odour of a good ſmelling ſauour. And the nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer hee drewe vnto his death, the more plainelye doeth the force and fruite of the Lorde his death ſhewe it ſelfe.<note n="p" place="margin">What we may learne by this myracle.</note> Certaynelie the Lorde ſheweth moſte manifeſtlie by this his ſixte laſt ſigne or miracle, that hee is the life of all the worlde, who although hee dyed vppon the croſſe, yet can hee ſaue the ſoules of the faithfull in death, and rayſe vp the dead. And becauſe this thing is harde to bee beleued of fleſhe and mans reaſon, this hiſtorie is handeled both plentifully, and exactly, yea and euidently, ſo that thou maieſt thinke, that thou beholdeſt all thinges with viewe of eye. In the meane ſeaſon in <hi>Martha</hi> and <hi>Marye</hi> wee are taught, what manner of faith ours ought to bee. And the myndes of the Godlye are confirmed through all the hiſtorye agaynſt the feare of death, the offence of the Croſſe is mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigated and vtterlie taken awaye,<note n="q" place="margin">From the 46 ver. vnto the end of the chapter.</note> and the cauſe of the hatred and enuie
<pb facs="tcp:19465:67"/> of the Prieſtes or Senatours of the people of Iſrael is declared, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they beeing blinded conſulte to kill Chriſte. That conſultation is touched in fewe, but yet in euident words.<note n="*" place="margin">The 12. cha.</note> 
               <note n="r" place="margin">In the 1, 2, 3, and 4. ver.</note> Now heereunto pertaineth the feaſt ſolemniſed in <hi>Bethanie,</hi>
               <note n="s" place="margin">From the 5. ver. vnto the 12</note> in the deſcription whereof, the cauſe is ſhewed whereby <hi>Iudas</hi> being moued, purpoſed to ſell and betray Ieſus to the Prieſtes.<note n="t" place="margin">The Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts purpoſe in the reſt, which followeth.</note> In thoſe things, whiche followe, <hi>Iohn</hi> handeleth thoſe matters, whereby the glory and vertue of Chriſte appeared &amp; ſhone oftentimes moſt cleere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the people of Iſrael:<note n="v" place="margin">From the 12. ver. vnto the 19</note> &amp; firſt, where as he entred into the citie w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> regal pompe, hee declareth, that he is the king &amp; the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerer of the people of God, whome the Prophetes foreſhewed to come.<note n="x" place="margin">In the 19. ver</note> This, greeued the Phariſees, who beeing ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed with the greatneſſe, power, and euidencie of Chriſt his doings, are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to deſpaire of their owne matters.<note n="y" place="margin">In the 20, 21 &amp; 22. ver.</note> Hereunto this alſo is added, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the <hi>Greekes</hi> or <hi>Gentiles</hi> came to <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> from cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries very farre diſtant to ſee and ſalute Ieſus.<note n="z" place="margin">From the 23. ver. vnto the 27</note> Whereby y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord taketh occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſpeake of his death, of the fruite there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
<pb facs="tcp:19465:68"/> and of the great and farre exceeding glory following his death immediately.<note n="a" place="margin">In the 27, and 28, ver.</note> Alſo he prayeth, that the father would ſet foorth his glory.<note n="b" place="margin">In the 28 and 29 ver.</note> An oracle is giuen from heauen anſwering to the prayers of the Lorde.<note n="c" place="margin">From the 30 ver. vnto the 34.</note> Therevpon the Lorde teacheth agayne moſt cleerely, what fruite ſhall come vnto the faithfull through his death.<note n="d" place="margin">In the 34, verſe.</note> Nowe when the people here upon moued a queſtion, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the eternitie of the <hi>Mesſias,</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">In the 35, and 36. ver.</note> Hee exhorteth them to faith.<note n="f" place="margin">In the 37. verſe.</note> The <hi>Iewes</hi> notwithſtanding continue in their vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe,<note n="g" place="margin">From the 38. ver. vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 44.</note> the which thing <hi>Iohn</hi> proueth that <hi>Eſaias</hi> foreſhewed.<note n="h" place="margin">Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the 44. verſe vnto the end of the chap.</note> But to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme the weake in faith, the Lord maketh a moſt vehement Sermon, wherein hee gathereth a briefe rehearſall of his doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, hytherto publikely propoſed.<note n="i" place="margin">What went before.</note> 
               <hi>S. Iohn</hi> hitherto hath ſet foorth thoſe things, which the Lorde ſpake and did, priuately and publikely, before his Paſſion, among thoſe which were familiar with him, and in the preſence of all the common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as well by diſputing as by preaching, both maintaining and deliuering to the Church the moſt full and perfect doctrine
<pb facs="tcp:19465:68"/> of the Goſpell:<note n="k" place="margin">What follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth.</note> but in thoſe thinges, which followe, hee deſcribeth certaine ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete and myſticall, as well ſayings as do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the Lorde, which hee ſpake and did, in that his laſt and myſticall Supper, before his Diſciples. Heere all thinges burne and glitter with a certaine diuine brightneſſe. For heere all the myſteries of our faith, and of the kingdome of God are propoſed and opened, and the moſt daintie banket of the ſoule and ſpirite, is moſt liberally furniſhed and ſet foorth by the Sonne of God himſelf to the Church, ſo that the faithfull hearer diligently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering theſe things, may ſeeme to heare not a humane, but a very diuine voyce, and not to be at any earthly ſupper, but being admitted into heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ſelfe, to bee a gueſt at God his table. Notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding paſſing ouer thoſe thinges, which the other three Euangeliſts handeled both diligently and ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tifully touching this laſt ſupper, <hi>Iohn</hi> ſetteth foorth moſt fully thoſe thinges, which hytherto were not committed to writing, leaſt the Church of Chriſt ſhould want any thing, but that it might haue a moſte full Hiſtorie of the affayres
<pb facs="tcp:19465:69"/> of her Sauiour.<note n="*" place="margin">The 13. cha.</note> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">In the firſt verſe.</note> Therefore in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning ſpeaking ſomewhat in maner of a Preface,<note n="m" place="margin">From the 2 ver. vnto the 12</note> hee bringeth in foorthwith the Lorde waſhing the Diſciples feete,<note n="n" place="margin">From the 12. ver. vnto the 18.</note> and commending by that deede, with cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine wordes added thereunto, both humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, and the duties of charitie, expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding alſo the effect or fruite of his paſſion.<note n="o" place="margin">From the 18 verſe vnto the 30.</note> After theſe things is placed a diligent and profitable diſputation of <hi>Iudas</hi> his treaſon.<note n="p" place="margin">In the 30. ver</note> When as <hi>Iudas</hi> was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted foorth of the holy banket of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> that hee might gather togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cutters, which might take Ieſus,<note n="q" place="margin">In the 31, &amp; 32. verſes.</note> Ieſus vnderſtood that his laſt houre now approched, he ſeeth alſo that his diſciples, beeing oppreſſed with great ſorowe, are diuerſly tempted and greeued,<note n="r" place="margin">Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the 33. verſe vnto the end of the chap.</note> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee maketh a worthie oration vnto them with great deliberation, that hee might thereby comforte his <hi>Diſciples,</hi> and admoniſhe them and fully inſtruct them in all his matters. For this are they wont to doe, which are at the point of death, namely to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort theirs, to inſtruct the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in diuers thinges, &amp; grauely to warne them. For in ſuche manner the Lorde
<pb facs="tcp:19465:69"/> maketh a large and a moſt profitable ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vnto his <hi>Diſciples</hi> heere put downe in writing vnto the 17. Chapter, which for the more plaineneſſe wee haue deuided into two partes. The former part is comprehended in the latter end of the<note n="s" place="margin">From the 33 verſe</note> 13 Chapter, and in the 14. Chapter through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out. The latter part is contained in the 15. and 16. Chapters. But the Orati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or Sermon of the Lorde is diuers, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it referred to any one, and certaine marke, except thou reſpect conſolation &amp; inſtruction. For all thinges tend here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, that the Diſciples of Chriſte be not troubled, and that they may vnderſtande the myſteries of Chriſte, and know what they ſhoulde doe.<note n="t" place="margin">In the 31, 32 and 33. verſes of the 13. chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</note> And firſt hee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treateth of his death, which becauſe it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vnto the worlde to bee ſhamefull and infamous, hee teacheth, that both the father and the ſonne is glorified through his death.<note n="v" place="margin">In the 34. &amp; 35. ver.</note> Then becauſe he muſt leaue them, leaſt they ſhoulde bee igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant howe to behaue themſelues, and what lawes they ſhoulde keepe one with another, hee doth not ouercharge them with many preſcriptions, but commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
<pb facs="tcp:19465:70"/> vnto them charitie only.<note n="x" place="margin">In the 36. &amp; 37. ver.</note> Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding heere the Lordes talke is broken of a litle, through the bolde bragge of Saint <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">In the 36.37, &amp; 38. ver.</note> which the Lorde cooling, goeth forwarde in his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe,<note n="*" place="margin">The 14. cha.</note>
               <note n="z" place="margin">In the 1 ver.</note> and profeſſeth openly that hee is very God, that hee may ſtay vp the faith of his Diſciples, wherein is the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt foundation of comfort.<note n="a" place="margin">From the 2. ver. vnto the 8.</note> He ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth that hee therefore departeth hence and dyeth, that hee may open the way for vs into heauen.<note n="b" place="margin">From the 8, ver. vnto the 15</note> Afterwardes he ſheweth <hi>Philip</hi> and the reſt more fully, that hee is in all thinges coequall and of one ſubſtance with the Father: yea and that the Father cannot be knowen but by the Sonne.<note n="c" place="margin">In the 15. ver</note> And nowe alſo hee exhorteth them to keepe his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements faithfully:<note n="d" place="margin">In the .16 and 17. verſes.</note> and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth an other comforter.<note n="e" place="margin">From the 18. ver. vnto the 25</note> More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer hee vſeth many reaſons, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by hee may both comfort their ſorowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full mindes, &amp; ſtirre them vp to the vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente ſtudie of godlideſſe.<note n="f" place="margin">From the 25 ver. vnto the 30</note> And heereupon hee reaſoneth more plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully of the comforter, or holy Ghoſt,<note n="g" place="margin">In the 30 and 31, ver.</note> and ſaith moſt plainely that he muſt
<pb facs="tcp:19465:70"/> ſhortly be deliuered into the handes of ſinnefull men: but yet ſo that the world ſhoulde bee ſaued thereby.<note n="h" place="margin">What went before.</note> Hauing finiſhed the former part of the Lorde Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Oration made after the Supper vnto his beloued Diſciples,<note n="i" place="margin">What follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</note> wee come nowe to the latter part, which ſeemeth to bee ſpoken in the iourney towarde the mount of Oliues, and is comprehended in the 15. and 16. Chapters.<note n="k" place="margin">How this which foloweth, agreeth with that which went before.</note> And it agreeth with thoſe thinges, which went before in this maner: The Lorde had oftentimes ſaide, that hee muſt departe foorth of this worlde to the Father, the meane while leaſt the Diſciples ſhoulde ſuppoſe, that they ſhoulde vtterly bee forſaken, hee added, that hee with the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the holy Ghoſt woulde come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, and abide with them, if they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in keeping his preceptes.<note n="*" place="margin">The 15 cha.</note>
               <note n="l" place="margin">From the 1. ver. vnto the 9.</note> Now as it were repeating y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame thing, &amp; after a ſort inlarging the ſame by bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the moſt elegant ſimilitude of the vine &amp; of the branches, he reaſoneth moſt plainely of his remaining, that I may ſo tearme it, or of his preſence in the
<pb facs="tcp:19465:71"/> Church, yea and of the true Communion of Chriſte and his Saintes, I meane, in that hee remaineth wholy in vs, by his ſpirite, by his power, and by his euident operation, if wee by faith and by loue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine in him.<note n="m" place="margin">From the 9. verſ. vnto 14.</note> And verily for this cauſe he intreateth more copiouſly of bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly loue.<note n="n" place="margin">In the 14, &amp; 15. verſes.</note> And by the way he rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoneth of the worthineſſe of the faithfull, whome hee calleth friendes, and not ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants.<note n="o" place="margin">In the 16. ver</note> Againe leaſt they ſhould be proude, he addeth, that this is beſtowed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them through the free election of God, which hath choſen them, that they may go and bring foorth plentifull fruite.<note n="p" place="margin">From the 17 ver. vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 26.</note> But the Diſciples began foorthwith to feele, what perilles they ſhoulde bee in, and therefore were they not a little afraide of themſelues. The Lorde therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming their mindes, reaſoneth much and diuerſly of the croſſe and of ſuffering,<note n="q" place="margin">In the 26 and 27, ver.</note> and promiſeth again the comforter, which ſhoulde ſtirre them vp, incourage, and confirme them in troubles &amp; perſecutions.<note n="*" place="margin">The 16. cha.</note> 
               <note n="r" place="margin">From the 1. ver. vnto the 16<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> Moreouer, hee diſputeth with muche profite many things concerning y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> effects and ſtrength of the comforter, ſhewing
<pb facs="tcp:19465:71"/> howe the holy ghoſt being giuen ſhoulde recompence his corporall preſence, which after his death ſhoulde be no whitte at all profitable vpon earth, howe by him he woulde prepare his Church in the world, and raigne in it.<note n="s" place="margin">From the 16 ver. vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 20.</note> And yet doth he agayne put them in remembraunce that hee muſt firſt die,<note n="t" place="margin">In the 20 ver.</note> and that herevpon his diſciples ſhoulde be oppreſſed with great ſorowe: whom forthwith rayſing vp againe by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting them, he aſſureth them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe ſhall not be long: but that the ioy, which ſhall riſe of his reſurrection, and fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe their ſorrow, ſhall be euerlaſting.<note n="v" place="margin">In the 21, and 22, ver.</note> And this doth he declare by the ſimilitude of a woman trauailing.<note n="x" place="margin">From the 23 ver. vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 28.</note> Moreouer leaſt they ſhoulde bee ouermuche ſorrowefull through the departing of his bodie into heauen, hee promiſeth his diſciples, that he will teach them all the ſecretes of the kingdome of God by his ſpirite, and that hee will giue them whatſoeuer they ſhall aſke in his name, that is to ſay, in the name of Chriſt:<note n="y" place="margin">In the 28 verſe.</note> and with all he gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth into a briefe ſumme the whole matter of our redemption, deſiring to faſten this deepe in their hearts.<note n="z" place="margin">In the 29 &amp; 30 verſes.</note> The which things
<pb facs="tcp:19465:72"/> when as the diſciples receiued with great reioycing, and commended, profeſſing, that they did now beleeue, and plainly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that he was the ſonne of God,<note n="a" place="margin">In the 31, and 32 ver.</note> he fortelleth them, that they ſhall forthwith forſake him, and euery one prouide for him ſelfe by fliyng away.<note n="b" place="margin">In the laſt ver.</note> And in the end, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding his whole talke continued hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to from the thirtienth Chapter, and ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiyng whereunto all things muſt be appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, hee ſaith: <hi>Theſe wordes haue I ſpoken vnto you, that in mee you might haue peace, for in the worlde yee haue tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation: but bee of good cheare, I haue ouercome the worlde.</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">What went before &amp; what foloweth.</note> After that our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt had partlie comforted his diſciples by theſe verie diuine ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and partly informed and inſtructed them againſt the ſtorme of euilles imminent, becauſe he had purpoſely warned them, that they muſt not put their truſt in any humane thinges, but in the helpe of God, he doth moreouer teach by his owne ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, that in their afflictions the looke no whither els, but to the Father of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note n="d" place="margin">From the 1. ver. vnto the 6.</note>
               <note n="*" place="margin">The 17. cha.</note> Now therefore preparing him ſelfe to
<pb facs="tcp:19465:72"/> ſuffer his paſſion, he beginneth it with making his prayers vnto the father, vnto whom firſt hee commendeth himſelfe,<note n="e" place="margin">From the 6, ver. vnto the 20</note> then his Apoſtles,<note n="f" place="margin">From the 20 ver. vnto the end of the chap.</note> laſtly all, whiche beleeue the doctrine of the Apoſtles, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching him, that hee woulde glorifie him, and that hee woulde guide the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and the Churche of the faythfull, through this moſt vnpure worlde, in the ſtudie of the trueth, of godlineſſe, and of charitie, and that he woulde ioyne them vnto him for euer.<note n="*" place="margin">The 18. cha.</note> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">In the 1.</note> Hauing finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his prayer, he goeth vnto the mount of <hi>Oliues,</hi> entring into a garden, where hee might commende him ſelfe agayne to God by his prayers.<note n="h" place="margin">In the 2. &amp; 3. verſes.</note> The meane while trayterous <hi>Iudas</hi> had gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither a bande of moſt wicked varlettes, and approcheth the innocent.<note n="i" place="margin">From the 4. ver. vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 10.</note> The Lord, that he might ſhewe that hee ſuffered of his owne accorde and willingly, and that he was omnipotent, although hee ſuffered him ſelfe to bee chayned, ouerthrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth often times the bande in the graden, and afterwardes committeth hym ſelfe voluntarily vnto the wicked to be bound.
<pb facs="tcp:19465:73"/> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">In the 10, and 11 verſes.</note> There <hi>Peter</hi> fighteth vnhappily enough, and was rebuked of his maiſter.<note n="l" place="margin">In the 12.13 and 14 ver.</note> They bring the Lorde foorthwith to <hi>Annas</hi> the high prieſt, and from him to <hi>Caiphas,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was placed that yere in the chiefe dignitie of prieſthood.<note n="m" place="margin">In the 19 ver</note> Inquiſition is made touching the doctrine of Ieſus,<note n="n" place="margin">In the 20, and 21, ver.</note> and whileſt he went about to anſwere,<note n="o" place="margin">In the 22.23, &amp; 24 ver.</note> he is moſt vnworthily beaten of a ſeruant of the high prieſts.<note n="p" place="margin">In the 15, 16 17, and 18. verſes, alſo in the 25, 26, and 27. verſes.</note> Whileſt theſe things were in doing, <hi>Peter</hi> denieth &amp; abiureth the Lorde moſt ſhamefully.<note n="q" place="margin">In the 28, verſe.</note> Chriſte is lead from the high prieſtes court ſtraight wayes vnto the deputies common hall of iudgement, becauſe he ſeemed worthie of death.<note n="r" place="margin">From the 29 ver. vnto the 38</note> He is accuſed before <hi>Pilate,</hi> and the chiefe pointes of the accuſation are diſcuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,<note n="t" place="margin">In the 38. and 39 verſes.</note> but <hi>Pilate</hi> finding no fault in him, goeth about by cunning too ſet him at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie.<note n="v" place="margin">In the laſt ver.</note> Which when it fell out vnlucke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,<note n="*" place="margin">The 19. chap</note> 
               <note n="x" place="margin">From the 1 ver. vnto the 6.</note> he bringeth him torne with whips, and crowned with a crowne of thornes, foorth vnto the common people a beaſt of many heades.<note n="y" place="margin">In the 6. ver.</note> They crie out together, that he may be crucified.<note n="z" place="margin">From the 7, ver. vnto the 12</note> But <hi>Pilate</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring of many things,<note n="a" place="margin">From the 12 ver. vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 16</note> yet at the laſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome with the wicked outcries of the
<pb facs="tcp:19465:73"/> Iewes,<note n="b" place="margin">In the 16 ver</note> deliuereth Ieſus to be crucified. He is receiued of the ſouldiers,<note n="c" place="margin">In the 17 ver.</note> and led foorth into a place named of dead mens ſkulles vnto execution.<note n="d" place="margin">In the 18 ver<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> There is he lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vp vpon a croſſe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> middeſt betweene two theeues.<note n="e" place="margin">From the 19 ver. vnto the 23</note> The title or cauſe of his death is put vpon the croſſe by <hi>Pilate</hi> not without great reaſoning and controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie.<note n="f" place="margin">In the 23, and 24, ver.</note> Moreouer the ſouldiers parte the Lordes garmentes, and caſt lottes for his coate, which was without ſeame, vnder the croſſe.<note n="g" place="margin">In the 25, 26, &amp; 27 ver.</note> The Lorde from the croſſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth his mother to <hi>Iohn:</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">In the 28 ver</note> Hee thirſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,<note n="i" place="margin">In the 29 ver</note> and refuſeth to drinke vineger offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him in a ſponge,<note n="k" place="margin">In the 30 ver.</note> and witneſſing ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lily that all things were finiſhed, and that the ſacrifice was perfect, hee gaue vp his ghoſt to God the father.<note n="l" place="margin">In the 31, and 32 ver.</note> Afterwardes the legges of the theeues are broken,<note n="m" place="margin">In the 33<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and 34. ver.</note> Ieſus his ſide is opened, blood and water guiſheth out of it.<note n="n" place="margin">In the 35, 36 &amp; 37 ver.</note> 
               <hi>Iohn</hi> which ſawe it, doth holily witneſſe the truth,<note n="o" place="margin">From the 38 ver. vnto the end of the chap.</note> And laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly come godly &amp; deuout men, whiche take downe the dead bodie of the Lorde from the croſſe, and ſpice it moſt honeſtly, and burie it.<note n="p" place="margin">What follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,</note> 
               <hi>Iohn,</hi> in this laſt part of his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, rekoneth vp, with great truſt and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence,
<pb facs="tcp:19465:74"/> the moſt manifeſt teſtimonies and proofes of the glorious reſurrection from the dead of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he ſheweth fully and plainely, that hee roſe againe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the dead truely w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his true &amp; liuely body. He was not very carefull touching the maner of the reſurrection, &amp; concerning the natural order of the reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations. For he ſawe that the other Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts had plentifully handled &amp; plainely enough ſet y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> forth therfore he ſetteth forth the moſt choſen proofes:<note n="*" place="margin">The 20. cha.</note> 
               <note n="q" place="margin">In the 1 ver. and from the 11. vnto the 18</note> And in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning he ſheweth, howe hee ſhewed him ſelf aliue to <hi>Marie Magdalen.</hi> For <hi>Marke</hi> alſo ſaith:<note n="r" place="margin">Marke chap. 16 ver. 9.</note> 
               <hi>When Ieſus was riſen early, the firſt day after the Sabboth, he appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red firſt to <hi>Marie Magdalen,</hi> out of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had caſt ſeuen deuils.</hi>
               <note n="s" place="margin">In the 2 and 18 verſe.</note> Nowe ſhee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth to the apoſtles forthwith what ſhe had ſeene:<note n="t" place="margin">From the 3 ver. vnto the 11</note> two of the whiche running to the ſepulchre, finde by certaine ſignes &amp; tokens, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhee had reported no vaine mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.<note n="v" place="margin">In the 19 and 20. verſes.</note> Now the Lord himſelfe, being wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to ſhewe manifeſtly his manifeſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection to the ten diſciples gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, commeth into the middeſt of them, &amp; ſheweth them openly his hands and ſide
<pb facs="tcp:19465:74"/> marked with the prints of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wounds, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſo the trueth of his true reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note n="x" place="margin">In the 21, 22. &amp; 23 ver.</note> Forthwith he committeth and inioyneth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtles the miniſterie of preaching ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation &amp; redemption, putting the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in truſt with the kayes of the kingdome of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note n="y" place="margin">In the 24. ver</note> Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe thinges were in doing, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſciples being aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bled in one place, <hi>Thomas</hi> onely was away,<note n="z" place="margin">In the 25 ver</note> vnto whom returning ſhortly afterwardes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſciples reioycing greatly, report y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they had ſeene the Lord. He ſuſpecting that they had bin deluded by ſome phantaſme, denieth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hee will beleeue, except he beholde the body of Ieſus openly with his owne eyes, yea and handeling it with his handes, touche the truth of his body.<note n="a" place="margin">In the 26. &amp; and 27. verſes</note> Therefore after eight dayes, when as all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eleuen diſciples were come togither againe into one place, the Lord Ieſus is preſent againe, and offereth himſelfe moſt manifeſtly to <hi>Thomas,</hi> both to be beholden of his eyes, &amp; to be handled of his hands,<note n="b" place="margin">From the 28. verſe vnto the end of the chap.</note> who being ouercome with the euidencie &amp; truth of the matter, crieth out, that hee doth nowe acknowledge and worſhip Chriſt for his Lord &amp; God.<note n="c" place="margin">Where theſe things were done.</note> And theſe things were done in the very citie of
<pb facs="tcp:19465:75"/> Hieruſalem, and about the verye graue of the Lord: the which although they might ſuffice fully to confirme the faith of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection,<note n="*" place="margin">The 21. chap</note> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">From the 1 ver. vnto the 15</note> yet doeth <hi>Iohn</hi> adde a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine notable proofe, whereby he declared in Galilee, that he was riſen from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dead, by dyning alſo w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his diſciples. For the Lord had promiſed, as well by his priuate promiſe, as by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> promiſes of Angels, that it ſhoulde come to paſſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhoulde ſee him in Galilee.<note n="e" place="margin">In the 15, 16 and 17 ver.</note> And vnto this reuelatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Iohn</hi> ioyneth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> talke which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord had w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Simo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Peter</hi> immediatly after dinner, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he reſtored to his miniſterie,<note n="f" place="margin">In the 18, &amp; 19 verſes.</note> foretelling him his ſorowfull deſtenie.<note n="g" place="margin">Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the 20 ver. vnto the 24</note> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueiling what ſhould become of <hi>Iohn,</hi> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euery one ought to looke vnto his own calling.<note n="h" place="margin">In the 24, &amp; laſt verſe of the chapter.</note> Laſtly <hi>Iohn,</hi> making a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath deſcribed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matters of our lord Ieſus very faithfully, ſhutteth vp the hiſtorie of the truth of the Goſpell.</p>
            <trailer>Here endeth the ſumme of the Goſpell by Saint Iohn.</trailer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:19465:75"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
